<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Songs of sundrie natures some of grauitie, and others of myrth, fit for all companies and voyces. Lately made and composed into musicke of 3.4.5. and 6. parts: and published for the delight of all such as take pleasure in the exercise of that art. By VVilliam Byrd, one of the Gentlemen of the Queenes Maiesties honorable chappell.</title>
            <author>Byrd, William, 1542 or 3-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 140 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B11892</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842700</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176435</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240898018</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 4256</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S106995</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99842700e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B11892)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176435)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 185:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Songs of sundrie natures some of grauitie, and others of myrth, fit for all companies and voyces. Lately made and composed into musicke of 3.4.5. and 6. parts: and published for the delight of all such as take pleasure in the exercise of that art. By VVilliam Byrd, one of the Gentlemen of the Queenes Maiesties honorable chappell.</title>
                  <author>Byrd, William, 1542 or 3-1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[268] p. : music  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas East, the assigne of William Byrd, and are to be sold at the house of the sayd T. East, being in Aldersgate streete, at the signe of the blacke Horse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589. Cum priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Six partbooks, each with separate dated title page. At head of title, part 1: "Superius."; part 2: "Medius."; part 3: "Contratenor."; part 4: "Tenor."; part 5: "Sextus."; part 6: "Bassus.".</note>
                  <note>Signatures: Superius, [A]2 B-H⁴; Medius, [A]2 B-D⁴; Contratenor, [A]2 B-F⁴; Tenor, [A]2 B-H⁴; Sextus, [A]2 B⁴ C² ; Bassus, [A]2 B-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Part-songs, English.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Part-songs, Sacred.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:2"/>
                  <p>SVPERIVS.</p>
                  <p>¶ Songs of sundrie natures, some of grauitie, and others of myrth, fit for all compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and voyces. Lately made and composed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Musicke of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts: and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished for the delight of all such as take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in the exercise of that Art.</p>
                  <p>By VVilliam Byrd, one of the Gentlemen of the Queenes Maiesties honorable Chappell.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device (?) not found in McKerrow</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Thomas East, the assigne of William Byrd, and are to be sold at the house of the sayd T. East, being in Aldersgate streete, at the signe of the blacke Horse. 1589.</p>
                  <p>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:3"/>
                  <head>To the right honorable my very good Lord, Sir Henry Carye. Baron of Hunsdon, knight of the most noble order of the Garter, Lord Chamberlen to the Queenes most excelent Maiestie, Lord Warden of the East Marches towards Scotland, gouernor of Barwycke and the Castle of Norham, Captaine of the Gentlemen Pencioners, Iustice in Oyer, ouer all her Maiesties Forrests and Chases, on this side the Riuer of Trent, &amp; one of her Maiesties most honorable priuie councell▪ William Byrd wisheth increase of honor, with all true felicitie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing obserued (Right Honorable) that since the publishing in print, of my last labors in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, diuers persons of great honor and worship, haue more esteemed &amp; delighted in the exercise of that Art, then before. And being perswaded, that the same hath the rather encreased, through their good acceptation of my former endeuors: it hath especially moued and encouraged me to take further paines to gratifie theyr curteous dispositions therevnto, knowing that the varietie and choyse of songs, is both a prayse of the Art, and a pleasure to the delighted therein. And finding no person to whome the dedication thereof so fitly and properly belonged, as vnto your Lordship, by whome (through the honorable office which you exercise about her Maiesties person) both my selfe (for my place of seruice,) &amp; all other her highnesse Musitions are to be commanded, and vnder your high aucthoritie to be protected. And for many fauors to me shewed, being most deepely bound vnto your Honor, hauing not in me any other powre of seruiseable thanckfulnesse then in notes &amp; tunes of Musicke. I most humbly beseech your Lordship to take into your Honorable protection, these my poore trauells in that Art, accepting them as seruants redy to giue your L. delight, after you haue bene forewearied in affayres of great importance. Besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching almightie God to giue you a long, healthie, and happie lyfe, with a blessed end. I humbly take my leaue.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Lordships most bounden, William Byrd.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_courteous_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:4"/>
                  <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Inding that my last Impression of Musicke (most gentle Reader) through thy curtesie and fauor, hath had good passage and vtterance: and that since the publishing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the exercise and loue of that Art to haue exceedingly encreased. I haue bene encouraged thereby, to take fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paines therein, and to make thee pertaker thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I would shew my selfe gratefull to thee for thy loue, and desirous to delight thee with varietie, whereof (in my opinion) no Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is more plentifully adorned then Musicke. For which purpose I do now publish for thee, songs of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts, to serue for all companies and voyces: whereof some are easie and plaine to sing, other more hard and difi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, but all, such as any yong practicioner in singing, with a little foresight, may easely performe. If I finde thy curtesie to extend aswell to these my present trauells, as it hath done to my former endeuors, I will make my selfe endebted to thee during my lyfe, of whatsoeuer is in me, to yeeld thy delight in Musick, any satisfaction.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The most affectionate freend to all that loue or learne Musick William Byrd.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="superius" type="partbook">
                  <div n="1" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:4"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Domine in furore.</hi> Psal. 6. I. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord in thy rage rebuke me not, for my most gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous sinne, nor in thine anger chasten me, but let me fa╌uour winne, fauour winne, but let me fa╌uour winne, haue mercy Lord on me, {repeat} because my state is weake to see, heale me O Lord, O Lord, O Lord, heale me O Lord, for that my bones, {repeat} are troubled sore in me. {repeat} {repeat} are troubled sore in me, in me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:5"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Beati quorum.</hi> Psal. 32. II. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight blest are they whose wicked sinnes, by God remit╌ted be, remitted be, and whose defaults are coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and whose defaults are couered, through his great clemency, {repeat} The man is blest, {repeat} to whom our Lord, {repeat} our Lord hath not imputed sinne, {repeat} imputed sinne, nor in his sprit, deceyte is found, {repeat} nor takes delight there in, delight there in, nor takes delight, there in, nor takes delight, nor takes delight there in, nor takes delight there in.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:5"/>
                     <head>O 3. voc. <hi>Domine ne.</hi> Psal. 38. III. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord in thy wrath correct me not, correct me not, nor in thy fu╌rie vexe, {repeat} giue teares, giue grace, giue penitence, {repeat} vnto my sinfull sexe, for that the arrowes of thy wrath, of thy wrath, are fixed in my hart, and thou hast layd thine hand on me, {repeat} and thou hast layd thine hand, on me, for my most iust de╌seart, for my most iust de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seart, iust de╌seart.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:6"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc <hi>Miserere mei Deus.</hi> Psal. 51. IIII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God which art most mercyfull, haue mercy Lord on me, on me, haue mercy Lord on me, according to thy mercy great, {repeat} let me relcaued be, {repeat} And put away my wickednesse, my wickednesse. And put away my wickednesse, which sundery waies hath beene, {repeat} according to the multitude, {repeat} of thy compassions seene. {repeat} according, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to the multitude, of thy compassions seene, {repeat} compassions seene.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:6"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Domine exaudi.</hi> Psal. 102. V. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord heare my prayer instantly, which I before thee make, before thee make, and let my cry, and let my crye come vn╌to thee, do not the same forsake, {repeat} Turne not away thy face from me, when troubles me oppresse, {repeat} op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse, each day, each day inclyne thine eare to me, and suc╌cour my dis╌tresse, and suc╌cour my dis╌tresse.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:7"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>De profundis</hi> Psal. 130. VI. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom depth of sinne, O Lord to thee I haue made hum╌ble cry, Lord heare my voice, my voice, make it assend vnto thy throne so hye, vnto the voyce of my request, pour'd out before thy sight, thy sight, pour'd out before thy sight, before thy sight, Lord let thine eares attentiue be, to heare me day and night. {repeat} to heare me, to heare me day and night, {repeat} day and night, day and night.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:7"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Domine exaudi.</hi> Psal. 143. VII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ttend mine humble prayer Lord, with thine at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue eare, {repeat} euen in thy truth, {repeat} and iustice Lord, vouchsafe my sute to heare, {repeat} And into iudgement enter not, {repeat} with thy poore seruant heere, {repeat} poore seruant heere, because none shalbe iustified and stand before thee cleere, because none shalbe iustifyed, and stand before thee cleere, because none shalbe iustified, and stand before the cleere, before thee cleere, and stand before thee cleere, and stand before thee cleere.</p>
                     <trailer>Heere endeth the seauen Psalmes.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:8"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. VIII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vsanna fayre sometime assaulted was, by two old men desiring their delight, their de╌light, which leude intent they thought to bring to passe, if not by tender loue, by tender loue, if not by tender loue, {repeat} by force and might, to whom she said, {repeat} if I your sute denye, you will me falsely accuse and make me dye, and make me dye, and make me dye. And if I graunt to that which you request, my chastity, shall then deflowred be, shall then deflowred be, my chastity shall then defloured be, which is so deere to me, that I detest, my lyfe, my lyfe,
<pb facs="tcp:176435:8"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> if it berefted be from me, from me, and rather would I dye, {repeat} of mine accord, of myne accord, ten thousand tymes, {repeat} then once offend our Lord, offend our Lord, then once offend our Lord.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:9"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. IX. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Nightingale so pea╌sant &amp; so gay, so plea╌sant and so gay, in greenewood groues, delights to make his dwelling, his dwelling, delights to make his dwelling, in fields to flye, to flye, chanting his roundelaye, {repeat} at lyberty, against the Cage rebel╌ling, against the Cage rebel╌ling. But my poore hart, my poore hart with sorowes ouer swelling, {repeat} through bondage vyle, bynding my freedome short, bynding my freedome short, bynding my freedome short, no plea╌sure takes, {repeat} in these his sports excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb facs="tcp:176435:9"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> nor in his song receiueth no com╌fort, nor in his song receiueth no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, nor in his song receiueth no com╌fort, nor in his song receiueth, nor in his song receiueth no com╌fort, no comfort.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:10"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. The first part. X. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen younglyngs first on Cupide fyxe their sight, their sight, and see him naked, blyndfold &amp; a boy, &amp; a boy, though bow &amp; shafts and fier╌brand be his might, yet weene they he can worke them none an╌noy, {repeat} worke them none an╌noy. And therefore with his purpill wings they play, for glorious semeth loue though light as fether, and when they haue done {repeat} they weene to skape a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, for blynd men say they, say they, shoote they know not whether. {repeat} they know not whether, not whether, shoote they know not whether, shoote they know not whether.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:10"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. The second part. XI. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt when by proofe they finde that he did see, {repeat} &amp; that his wound did rather dym their sight, they wonder more how such a lad as he, should be of such surpassing powre &amp; myght: and might, and might, should be of such surpassing powre and might, {repeat} but Ants haue gals, {repeat} haue gals, so hath the Bee his styng, {repeat} then sheeld me heauens from such a subtyle thing, a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyle thing, then sheeld me heauens from such a subtyle thing, then sheeld &amp;c. then sheeld me heauens from such asubtyle thing, a sub╌tyle thing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:11"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. The first part. XII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ppon a Sommers day loue went to swym, and cast himselfe into a Sea of teares, into a Sea of teares, the clouds cald in their light, and heauen waxt dym, and sighes did raise a tempest, causing feares, {repeat} a tempest causing feares. The naked boy, could not so wyld his armes, {repeat} but that the waues were maisters of his might, &amp; threatned him to worke farre greater harmes, farre grea╌ter harmes, if he deuysed not to skape by flyght. {repeat}</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:11"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. The second part. XIII. SVPERIVS</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hen for a bote his quiuer stoode in stead, his bow vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent did serue him for a mast, whereby to sayle his cloth of vayle he spread, he spread, {repeat} his shafts for ores on either bord he cast, {repeat} on either bord he▪ cast, from shypwracke safe this wag got thus to shore, {repeat} got thus to shore, and sware, &amp; sware, to bath in louers teares no more, {repeat} in louers teares no more.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:12"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. XIIII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He greedy Hawke, with sooden sight of lure, of lure, with sooden sight, with sooden sight of lure doth stoope, doth stoope, in hope to haue her wished pray, so many men do stoope, to sights vnsure, {repeat} to sights vn╌sure, and courteous speach doth keepe them at the bay, {repeat} let them beware, {repeat} least frendly lookes be lyke, be like the lure▪ whereat the so╌ring Hawke did strike. whereat the so╌ryng Hawke did strike, did strike, whereat the so╌ring Hawke, the soring Hawke did strike.</p>
                     <trailer>Heere endeth the songs of three parts.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:12"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The first part. XV. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S loue a boy? what meanes he then to strike, {repeat} or is he blind? why will he be a guide, is he a man? {repeat} why doth he hurt his lyke, {repeat} is he a God? {repeat} why doth he men de╌ride, {repeat} why doth he men de╌ryde, de╌ryde, deryde: No one of these but one compact of all, {repeat} a wilful boy, a man stil dealing blowes, of purpose blind, {repeat} to leade men to their thrall, {repeat} a God that rules, {repeat} vnruly, God he knowes, {repeat} vnruly, God he knowes, God he knowes, God he knowes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:13"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The second part. XVI. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Oy pittye me y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> am a child againe, {repeat} blynde be no more, {repeat} my guide to make me stray, to make me stray, man vse thy might to force away my paine, {repeat} {repeat} God do me good, {repeat} and leade me to my way, {repeat} {repeat} And if thou beest a powre to me vn╌knowne, powre of my life, let heere thy grace be showne, let {repeat} let heere thy grace be showne. And if &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:13"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The first part. XVII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ounded I am and dare not seeke reliefe, for this new stroke vnseene but not vnfelt, no bloud nor bruse is witnes of my griefe, is witnes of my griefe, but sighes, {repeat} and teares wherewith I mourne and melt, {repeat} wherwith I mourne and melt, if I complayne, my witnes is suspect, if I containe, with cares I am vndone, sit still and dye, tell truth and be reiect, tell truth and be reiect, O hatefull, O hatefull choyse that sorow cannot shunne, {repeat} that sorow cannot shun.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:14"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The second part. XVIII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Et of vs twaine whose losse shalbe the lesse, myne of my life, or you of your good name, or you of your good name, light is my death regarding my distresse, regarding my destresse, but your offence cryes out, cryes out to your diffame, to your diffame, A virgin fayre hath slayne for lacke of grace, of grace, the man that made an Idoll of her face, {repeat} of her face, of her face. A virgin. &amp;c</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:14"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The first part. XIX. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom Citheron: And smiling sits vppon a virgins lap, a virgins lap, thereby to traine poore misers to the trappe, whom beauty drawes with fancye to be fedde, {repeat} to be fedde, and when desire, and when desire, with eager lookes is ledde, then from her eyes, the arrow flyes, fethered with flame, arm'd with a golden head, {repeat} arm'd with a golden head.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:15"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The second part. XX. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here carelesse thoughts are freed of that flame, wherwith her thrales are scorched to the hart, to the hart, if loue would so, {repeat} would God, th' enchauntyng dart, might once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne &amp; burne, {repeat} from whence it came, from whence it came, not to deface, {repeat} of beautyes worke the frame, but by re╌bownd, it might be found, {repeat} what secret smart I suffer by the same▪ by the same, what secret smart I suffer by the same, I suffer by the same.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:15"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The third part. XXI. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F loue be iust, then iust is my desire, and if vniust, why is he calld a God, O God, O good, O good, O iust, reserue thy rod, {repeat} to chasten those that from thy lawes retyre, retyre, retyre, but chuse aryght, {repeat} good loue I thee require, require, the golden head, not that of lead, of lead, not that of lead, her hart is frost and must dissolue by fire, {repeat} her hart is frost and must dis╌solue by fire, dis╌solue by fire, and must dissolue by fyre, by fire.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:16"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord my God, let flesh and bloud thy seruant not subdew, nor let the world de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue me, with his glory most vntrue, vn╌true, let not O Lord, O myghty God, let not thy mor╌tall foe, let not the feend, let not the fende with all his craft, with all his craft, thy seruant, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw: But to resist, but to resist, giue fortitude, giue patience to en╌dure, giue Constancye, that alwaies thine I may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se╌uer sure, I may perse╌uer sure, perse╌uer
<pb facs="tcp:176435:16"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> sure, perseuer sure, I may perse╌uer sure, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seuer sure.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:17"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXIII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hyle that the Sunne with his beames hot, scorched the fruits in vale &amp; moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: Philon the sheperd late forgot, sitting besides a Christall fountaine, sitting besides a Christall fountaine, in shadow of a greene Oke tree, vppon his pipe this song playd he: vntru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oue, vntrue loue, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true loue, adew loue, adew loue, your minde is light, {repeat}
<pb facs="tcp:176435:17"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> your minde is light, soone lost, soone lost for new loue, soone lost for new loue.</p>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <head>2</head>
                        <l>So long as I was in your sight,</l>
                        <l>I was as your hart, your soule, your treasure,</l>
                        <l>And euermore you sob'd, you sigh'd,</l>
                        <l>Burning in flames beyond all measure,</l>
                        <l>Three dayes endur'd your Loue to me,</l>
                        <l>And it was lost in other three.</l>
                        <l>Adew Loue adew loue vntrue loue,</l>
                        <l>Vntrue loue vntrue loue adew loue,</l>
                        <l>Your mynd is light, soone lost for new loue</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <head>3</head>
                        <l>Another shepherd you dyd see,</l>
                        <l>To whome your hart was soone enchayned,</l>
                        <l>Full soone your loue was leapt from me,</l>
                        <l>Full soone my place he had obtayned,</l>
                        <l>Soone came a third your loue to winne,</l>
                        <l>And we were out and he was in.</l>
                        <l>Adew loue, &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="4">
                        <head>4</head>
                        <l>Sure you haue made me passing glad,</l>
                        <l>That you your mynd so soone remoued,</l>
                        <l>Before that I the leysure had,</l>
                        <l>To chuse you for my best beloued.</l>
                        <l>For all my loue was past and doonne,</l>
                        <l>Two dayes before it was begoonne.</l>
                        <l>Adew Loue &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:18"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXIIII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eioyce, re╌ioyce, with hart and voyce, with hart and voyce, in Christ his byrth this day, this day re╌ioyce, reioyce, re╌ioyce, in Christ his birth this day, this day, this day reioyce, re╌ioyce, reioyce, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, reioyce, reioyce, re╌ioyce, re╌ioyce, re╌ioyce.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:18"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXV. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ast of all doubtfull care, all doubtfull care, exile and ba╌nish teares, to ioyfull newes de╌uine, deuine, to ioyfull newes de╌uine, de╌uine, to ioyfull newes de╌uine, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, lend vs your listning eares. lend vs your list<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning eares, {repeat} lend vs your listning eares, lend vs your listning eares, your listning eares.</p>
                     <trailer>¶ <hi>Heere endeth the songs of foure parts.</hi>
                     </trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:19"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVI. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Eping full sore, {repeat} with face as fayre as siluer, not wanting rose nor lilly white to paint it, I saw a lady walke, {repeat} fast by a riuer, vppon whose bankes Dianaes Nimphes all dawnced, {repeat} her beauty great, {repeat} had diuers gods inchaunted, among the which loue was the first transformed, who vnto her his bow, {repeat} and shafts had graunted, and by her sight, to adament was turned. {repeat} Alas quoth I, alas quoth I, what meaneth this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanure, so faire a dame to be so full of sorowe: No wonder quoth a Nimphe,
<pb facs="tcp:176435:19"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> she wanteth pleasure, {repeat} her teares and sighes, {repeat} neceasse from eaue to morow: This lady, {repeat} Rich is of the gifts of beauty, but vnto her, are gifts of fortune daynty. are gifts of fortune daynty. This lady &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:20"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Enelope that longed for the sight, that longed for the sight, of her Vlisses, wandryng all to long, to long, felt neuer ioy, wherein she tooke delyght, although she lyu'd in greatest ioyes among, so I, so I poore wretch, posessing that I craue, that I craue, both liue and lacke, by wrong of that I haue, by wrong of that I haue: Then blame me not, {repeat} although to heauens, I cry, and pray the gods, {repeat} that shortly I might dye, that shortly I myght dye, that I might dye: Then blame me not, {repeat} although to heauens I cry, and pray the gods, that shortly I
<pb facs="tcp:176435:20"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> might dye, {repeat} that I might dye, {repeat} that I might dye, {repeat} that I myght dye.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:21"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVIII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ompell the Hawke to sitt that is vnmand, or make the Hound vntaught, to draw the Deere, {repeat} or bring the free, or bring the free against his will in band, or moue the sad a plea╌sant tale to heare {repeat} your time is lost, and you are neare the neere, {repeat} and you are neare the neere: So loue ne learnes by force the knot to knit, the knot to knit, he serues but those that feele sweete fancyes fit, he serues but those that feele sweete fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies sit, So loue ne learnes by force the knot to knit to knit, to knit, the
<pb facs="tcp:176435:21"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> knot to knit, he serues but those that feele sweete fan╌cyes fitt, sweete fancies fitt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:22"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXIX. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ee, see, those sweet eyes, those more then sweetest eyes, eyes whom the starres exceede not in their grace: See, see Loue at gaze, Loue that faine would de╌uise, but cannot speake to plead his wonderous case.</p>
                     <argument>
                        <p>The second part of this song, (<hi>Loue would discharge</hi>) is placed the XXXIIII. song.</p>
                     </argument>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:22"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXX. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> WHen I was otherwise then now I am, I loued more but skilled not so much fayre wordes &amp; smyles, could haue contented than, my simple age, {repeat} &amp; ignorance was such: But at the length, {repeat} experiēce made me wonder, that harts &amp; tongues did lodge so farre assunder, but at the length, {repeat} experience made me wonder, that harts &amp; tongues did lodge so farre assunder, that harts &amp; tongues, did lodge so farre assunder.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>As watermen which on the Teames do row</l>
                        <l>Looke to the East, but West keepes on the way,</l>
                        <l>My Soueraigne sweet, her countenance setled so,</l>
                        <l>To feede my hope while she her snares might laye.</l>
                        <l>And when she saw, that I was in her danger,</l>
                        <l>Good God, how soone she proued then a ranger.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I could not choose but laugh although to late,</l>
                        <l>To see great craft diszifered in a toye,</l>
                        <l>I loue her still, but such conditions hate,</l>
                        <l>Which so prophanes my Paradice of ioy.</l>
                        <l>Loue whetts the witts, whose paine is but a pleasure,</l>
                        <l>A toy, by fitts, to play withall at leasure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:23"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXI. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen first by force of fatal destenie, frō Carthage towne the Troian knight dyd sayle, Queene Dido fayre, with wofull weeping eye, his strange depart did greuously bewaile, And when no sighes nor teares could ease her smart, with sword ful sharp, {repeat} she pearst, she pearst her ten╌der hart. And when &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:23"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thought that loue had beene a boy, with blynded eyes, or else some other wanton toy, that men deuise, like tales of fayryes often told, by doting age that dyes for cold, lyke tales of fayryes often told, by doting age that dyes for cold, by doting age that dyes for cold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:24"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXIII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Deere life when may it be, that mine eyes thine eyes may see, and in them my minde discouer, whether absence hath had force, thy remembrance to deforce, from the Image of thy louer, from the Image of thy louer.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O, if I my selfe finde not,</l>
                        <l>though my parting ought forgot</l>
                        <l>Nor debard from beauties treasure</l>
                        <l>Let no tongue aspier to tell</l>
                        <l>In what hie Ioyes I shall dwell,</l>
                        <l>Onely thought aymes at the pleasure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thought therefore I will send thee</l>
                        <l>To take vp the place for me,</l>
                        <l>Long I will not after tary,</l>
                        <l>There vnseene thou maist be bold</l>
                        <l>These faire wonders to behold,</l>
                        <l>Which in them my hopes do cary.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:24"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXIIII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oue, loue would discharge, the dewty of his hart, in beauties praise, whose greatnes doth de╌nye, wordes words to his thoughts, &amp; thoughts to her de╌sart, which high conceyts since nothing can sup╌ply, Loue heere contraynd, through conquest to con╌fesse, byds silence sighe, that tongue cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse. Loue heere &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:25"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXV. SVPERIVS. A Carowle for Christmas day, the quire whereof (Reioyce) being of 4. parts, is the XXIIII. song.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> FRom Virgins wombe, &amp;c. </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>FRom Virgins wombe this day did spring,</l>
                        <l>The precious seed that saued man,</l>
                        <l>This day let man reioyce and sweetly sing</l>
                        <l>Since on this day saluacion first began,</l>
                        <l>This day dyd Christ mans soule from death remoue</l>
                        <l>With glorious Saints to dwell in heauen aboue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>This day to man came pledge of perfect peace,</l>
                        <l>This day to man came loue and vnitie,</l>
                        <l>This day mans griefe began for to surcease,</l>
                        <l>This day dyd man receiue a remedie,</l>
                        <l>For each offence and euery deadly sinne,</l>
                        <l>With guiltie hart that earst he wandred in.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>In Christ his flock let loue be surely plast,</l>
                        <l>From Christ his flock let concord hate expell,</l>
                        <l>Of Christ his flock let loue be so embrast,</l>
                        <l>As we in Christ, and Christ in vs may dwell,</l>
                        <l>Christ is the Author of sweet vnitie,</l>
                        <l>From whence procedeth all felicitie.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O sing vnto this glittering glorious king,</l>
                        <l>O praise his name let euery liuing thing,</l>
                        <l>Let hart and voyce like bells of siluer ring,</l>
                        <l>The comfort that this day to man doth bring,</l>
                        <l>Let Lute, let Shalme, with sound of sweet delight,</l>
                        <l>These ioyes of Christ his birth this day resight.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:25"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. The first part. XXXVI. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F gold all burnisht, and brighter then sunne beames, were those curled lookes vppon her noble head, from whose deepe conceits, my true deseruings flead, wherfore these mine eyes, such store of teares, such store of teares out streames, Her eyes are faire starrs, her red like damaske rose, her white siluer shyne of Moone, on Chris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall streame, her beauty perfect, wheron my fancies dreame, her lipps are rubies, her teeth of pearle, her teeth of pearle two rowes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="37" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:26"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. The second part. XXXVII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> HEr breath is more sweet then perfect Amber is, her yeeres are in prime, and nothing doth she want, that might drawe Angells from Heauen {repeat} to further blisse, to further blisse, {repeat} of all things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, this do I most complaine, her hart is a rock made all of Adamant, which guifts all delight, delight which guifts all delight, this last doth one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paine, {repeat} doth onely paine, {repeat} this last doth onely paine.</p>
                     <trailer>Heere endeth the songs of 5. parts.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="38" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:26"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XXXVIII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold how good a thing it is, {repeat} it is, it is, for bretheren to agree, {repeat} for to agree, when men amongst them do no stryfe, but peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord see, and concord see, full lyke vnto the pretious balme, full like vnto, full lyke vnto the pretious balme, from Arons head that fell, that fell, from Arons hed that fell, that fell, and did descend vppon his beard, his garment skirts vntyll, vn╌tyll, his garment skyrts vn╌tyll.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="39" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:27"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XXXIX. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND as the pleasant morning dew, the pleasant morning dew, the Mountaines doth releeue, doth releeue, the Mountaines doth releeue, {repeat} so God will blesse, where concord is, where concord is, So God will blesse where concord is, where concord is, and lyfe eter╌nall giue, eternall giue, and lyfe eternall giue, {repeat} {repeat} and lyfe eter╌nall giue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="40" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:27"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. XL. SVPERIVS. A Carowle for Christmas day, the quire whereof (Cast of all doubtfull care) being of 4. parts, is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> XXV. song.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Case of claye contaynd a crowne immortall, Redeem'd poore man, whose race before was thrall, to death, to doome, to paines of euerlasting, by his sweete death, {repeat} skornes, stripes, and of╌ten fasting, skornes, stripes, and of╌ten fasting.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>AN earthly tree a heauenly fruit it bare,</l>
                        <l>A case of clay containd a crowne immortall,</l>
                        <l>A crowne of crownes, a king whose cost &amp; care</l>
                        <l>Redeemd poore man, whose race before was thrall</l>
                        <l>To death, to dome, to paines of euerlasting,</l>
                        <l>By his sweet death, skornes, strypes, &amp; often fasting.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Starre aboue the Starres, a Sonne of light,</l>
                        <l>Whose blessed beames this wretched earth bespred</l>
                        <l>With hope of Heauen and of Gods sonne the sight</l>
                        <l>Which in our flesh and sinfull soule lay dead,</l>
                        <l>O fayth, O hope, O ioyes renownd for euer,</l>
                        <l>O liuely lyfe that deathlesse shall perseuer.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then let vs sing the Iollabyes of sleepe,</l>
                        <l>To this sweet babe, borne to awake vs all,</l>
                        <l>From drowsie sinne that made old Adam weepe,</l>
                        <l>And by his fault gaue to mankinde the fall,</l>
                        <l>For loe this day, the byrth day day of dayes,</l>
                        <l>Somons our songs to giue him laud &amp; praise.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="41" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:28"/>
                     <head>Of 6. A Dialogue betwen two Sheperds. XLI. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho made: Sweet beautie which hath powre to bowe the gods aboue. I, such as hath no peere, I gesse. Siluana fayre of high de╌sart, whome I loue best, yet loue I must, or else I dye. yet loue I must or else I dye, I dye, or else I dye, I dye.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="42" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:28"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XLII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> And think ye Nimphes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:29"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XLIII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oue is a fit of pleasure, bread out of Idle braynes, his fācies haue no measure, no more thē haue his paines: his vaine affections lyke the wether, lyke the wether, precise or fond, we wot not whether▪ we wot not wether.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="44" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:29"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. XLIIII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> IF in thine hart thou nourish will and giue all to thy lust, then sorowes sharpe &amp; griefes at length, endure of force thou must: but if that reason rule thy will, rule thy will, and gouerne all thy minde, {repeat} a blessed life then shalt thou leade, then shalt thou leade, a blessed lyfe then shalt thou leade, and fewest daungers finde, daungers finde, and fewest daungers finde, {repeat} and fewest daungers finde, {repeat} and fewest daungers finde.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="45" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:30"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. XLV. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto the hills myne eyes I lyft, myne eyes I lyft, vnto the hills mine eyes I lyft, my hope shall neuer fade, but from the Lord I looke for helpe, for helpe, that heauen and earth hath made: {repeat} hath made, hath made, Thy foote he will from slipping saue, &amp; he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> doth thee keepe, thee keepe, with watchfull eye will thee preserue, will thee preserue, without slomber or sleepe, or sleepe, without slomber or sleepe. The Lord thy keeper &amp; shade is, &amp; stands at thy right arme, the Sunne by day shall not thee burne, nor Moone by nyght thee harme. The Lord shall keepe thee from all yll, shall keepe thee
<pb facs="tcp:176435:30"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> from all yll, thy soule he shall pre╌serue, {repeat} and all thy waies both in &amp; out, for euer shall conserue, for euer shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue, {repeat} for euer shall con╌serue, {repeat} shall con╌serue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="46" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:31"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XLVI. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> CHrist rising, Christ rising agayne from the dead, now dyeth not, now dyeth not, dy╌eth not, Death from henceforth, Death from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth hath no power vppon him, for in that he dy'd, he dy'd but once to put away sinne, to put away sinne, to put away sinne, but in that he lyu╌eth, he lyueth vnto God, he lyueth vnto God, vn╌to God, In Christ Iesus our Lord, in Christ Iesus our Lord, In Christ Iesus our Lord.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="47" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:31"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XLVII. SVPERIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> CHrist is risen againe, the first fruits of them that sleepe, foreseeing, that by man came death, came death, foreseeing, that by man came death, came death, by man also, by man also commeth the resurrection of the dead, of the dead, For as by Adam, Adam, all men do dye, all men do dye, do dye, so by Christ, so by Christ, all men shalbe restored, all men shalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored, shalbe restored to lyfe, {repeat} restored to lyfe, to lyfe, to lyfe, to lyfe. So by Christ, so by Christ, by Christ, all men shalbe restored to lyfe, {repeat} restored to life, restored to life, to lyfe, restored to lyfe. A╌men.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:32"/>
                  <head>¶ <hi>A Table of all the songs contained in these Bookes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 3. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>LOrd in thy rage. I</item>
                        <item>Right blest are they. II</item>
                        <item>Lord in thy wrath. III</item>
                        <item>O God which art most mercifull. IIII</item>
                        <item>Lord heare my prayer instantly. V</item>
                        <item>From depth of sinne O Lord. VI</item>
                        <item>Attend myne humble prayer Lord. VII</item>
                        <item>Susanna fayre. VIII</item>
                        <item>The Nightingale. IX</item>
                        <item>When yonglings first. 1 part. X</item>
                        <item>But when by proofe. 2 part. XI</item>
                        <item>Vppon a sommers day. 1 part. XII</item>
                        <item>Then for a bote. 2 part. XIII</item>
                        <item>The greedy Hauke. XIIII</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 4. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>IS Loue a boy. 1 part. XV</item>
                        <item>Boy pittie mee. 2 part. XVI</item>
                        <item>Wounded I am. 1 part. XVII</item>
                        <item>Yet of vs twaine. 2 part. XVIII</item>
                        <item>From Citheron. 1 part. XIX</item>
                        <item>There carelesse thoughts 2 part. XX</item>
                        <item>If Loue be iust. 3 part. XXI</item>
                        <item>O Lord my God. XXII</item>
                        <item>While that the Sunne. XXIII</item>
                        <item>Reioyce, reioyce. XXIIII</item>
                        <item>Cast of all doubtfull care▪ XXV</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 5. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>WEeping full sore. XXVI</item>
                        <item>Penelope. XXVII</item>
                        <item>Compell y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Hauke to sit. XXVIII</item>
                        <item>See, see those sweet eyes. XXIX</item>
                        <item>When I was otherwise then now I am. XXX</item>
                        <item>When first by force. XXXI</item>
                        <item>I thought that loue had bene a boy. XXXII</item>
                        <item>O deere lyfe when may it be. XXXIII</item>
                        <item>Loue would discharge. XXXIIII</item>
                        <item>From Virgins wombe. XXXV</item>
                        <item>Of gold all burnisht. 1. part. XXXVI</item>
                        <item>Her breath is more sweet. 2. part. XXXVII</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 6. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>BEhold how good a thing it is. 1 part. XXXVIII</item>
                        <item>And as the pleasant mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dew. 2 part. XXXIX</item>
                        <item>An earthly tree. XL</item>
                        <item>Who made thee Hob. XLI</item>
                        <item>And think ye Nymphes. 1. part. XLII</item>
                        <item>Loue is a fit of pleasure. 2. part. XLIII</item>
                        <item>If in thine hart. XLIIII</item>
                        <item>Vnto the hills. XLV</item>
                        <item>Christ rising againe. 1 part. XLVI</item>
                        <item>Christ is risen againe. 2. part. XLVII</item>
                     </list>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London by Thomas East, dwelling in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dersgate streete, at the signe of the blacke Horse.</hi> 1589.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:32"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:33"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:33"/>
                  <p>MEDIVS.</p>
                  <p>¶ Songs of sundrie natures, some of grauitie, and others of myrth, fit for all compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and voyces. Lately made and composed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Musicke of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts: and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished for the delight of all such as take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in the exercise of that Art.</p>
                  <p>By VVilliam Byrd, one of the Gentlemen of the Queenes Maiesties honorable Chappell.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device (?) not found in McKerrow</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Thomas East, the assigne of William Byrd, and are to be sold at the house of the sayd T. East, being in Aldersgate streete, at the signe of the blacke Horse. 1589.</p>
                  <p>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:34"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:34"/>
                  <head>To the right honorable my very good Lord, Sir Henry Carye, Baron of Hunsdon, knight of the most noble order of the Garter, Lord Chamberlen to the Queenes most excelent Maiestie, Lord Warden of the East Marches towards Scotland, gouernor of Barwycke and the Castle of Norham, Captaine of the Gentlemen Pencioners, Iustice in Oyer, ouer all her Maiesties Forrests and Chases, on this side the Riuer of Trent, &amp; one of her Maiesties most honorable priuie councell. William Byrd wisheth increase of honor, with all true felicitie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing obserued (Right Honorable) that since the publishing in print, of my last labors in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, diuers persons of great honor and worship, haue more esteemed &amp; delighted in the exercise of that Art, then before. And being perswaded, that the same hath the rather encreased, through their good acceptation of my former endeuors: it hath especially moued and encouraged me to take further paines to gratifie theyr curteous dispositions therevnto, knowing that the varietie and choyse of songs, is both a prayse of the Art, and a pleasure to the delighted therein. And finding no person to whome the dedication thereof so fitly and properly belonged, as vnto your Lordship, by whome (through the honorable office which you exercise about her Maiesties person) both my selfe (for my place of seruice,) &amp; all other her highnesse Musitions are to be commanded, and vnder your high aucthoritie to be protected. And for many fauors to me shewed, being most deepely bound vnto your Honor, hauing not in me any other powre of seruiseable thanckfulnesse then in notes &amp; tunes of Musicke. I most humbly beseech your Lordship to take into your Honorable protection, these my poore trauells in that Art, accepting them as seruants redy to giue your L. delight, after you haue bene forewearied in affayres of great importance. Besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching almightie God to giue you a long, healthie, and happie lyfe, with a blessed end. I humbly take my leaue.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Lordships most bounden, William Byrd.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_courteous_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:35"/>
                  <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Inding that my last Impression of Musicke (most gentle Reader) through thy curtesie and fauor, hath had good passage and vtterance: and that since the publishing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the exercise and loue of that Art to haue exceedingly encreased. I haue bene encouraged thereby, to take fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paines therein, and to make thee pertaker thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I would shew my selfe gratefull to thee for thy loue, and desirous to delight thee with varietie, whereof (in my opinion) no Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is more plentifully adorned then Musicke. For which purpose I do now publish for thee, songs of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts, to serue for all companies and voyces: whereof some are easie and plaine to sing, other more hard and difi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, but all, such as any yong practicioner in singing, with a little foresight, may easely performe If I finde thy curtesie to extend aswell to these my present trauells, as it hath done to my former endeuors, I will make my selfe endebted to thee during my lyfe, of whatsoeuer is in me, to yeeld thy delight in Musick, any satisfaction.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The most affectionate freend to all that loue or learne Musick William Byrd.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="medius" type="partbook">
                  <div n="26" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:35"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVI. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Eping full sore, {repeat} with face as fayre as siluer, with face as fayre as siluer, not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting rose nor lilly white to paint it, to paint it, I saw a lady walke fast by a riuer, by a riuer, a riuer, vppon whose bankes Dianaes Nimphes all dawnced, {repeat} Dianaes Nimphes all dawnced, {repeat} her beauty great, {repeat} had diuers gods inchaūted, {repeat} among the which loue was the first transformed, the first transformed, who vnto her his bow and shafts had graunted, and shafts had graunted, had graunted, and by her sight, to adamant was turned, to adamant
<pb facs="tcp:176435:36"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> was turned, {repeat} {repeat} Alas quoth I, {repeat} what meaneth this demeanure, so faire a dame to be so full of sorowe, so full of sorow: No wonder quoth a Nimphe, quoth a Nimphe, she wanteth, pleasure, {repeat} her teares and sighes, {repeat} neceasse from eaue to morow, neceasse from eaue to morow: This lady, this lady Rich is of the gifts of beauty, the gifts of bewty, but vnto her are gifts of fortune daynty. but vnto her are gifts of fortune daynty. This lady &amp;c</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:36"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVII. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> PEnelope that longed for the sight, of her Vlisses, wandring all to long, felt neuer ioy wherein she tooke delyght, although she liu'd in greatest ioyes among, so I, so I poore wretch, possessing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I craue, both liue &amp; lacke, by wrong of that I haue: Then blame me not, {repeat} although to heauens I crye, I crye, and pray the gods, {repeat} that shortly I might dye, {repeat} Then blame me not, {repeat} although to heauens I cry, I cry, and pray the gods, {repeat} that shortly I might dye, {repeat} that I might dye, that I might dye, that I might dye, that I myght dye.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:37"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVIII. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ompell the Hauke to sit that is vn╌mand, or make the Hound vntaught, to draw the Deere, or bring the free against his will, or bring the free against his will in band, in band, or moue the sad, a plea╌sant tale to heare, your tyme is lost, and you are neare the neere, neare the neere, and you are neare the neere, are neare the neere. and you are neare the neere. So Loue, ne learnes by force the knot to knit, to knit, to knit, the knot to knit, he serues but those that feele sweete fan╌cies fitt, sweete fancies fitt. So Loue, ne learnes by force the
<pb facs="tcp:176435:37"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> knot to knit, the knot to knit, he serues but those that feele sweete fancies fitt. he serues but those that feele sweet fan╌cies fitt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:38"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXIX. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ee, see those sweet eyes, see those sweetest eyes, those more then sweetest eyes, with whome the starres exceede not in their grace. See Loue at gaze, {repeat} loue that faine, that faine would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise, deuise, but cannot speake to plead, to plead his wondrous case. his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous case.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:38"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXX. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> WHen I was otherwise then now, then now I am, I loued more, but skilled not so much, fayre words &amp; smyles, could haue, could haue cōten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted than, my symple age, my simple age, my simple age &amp; ignorance was such, and ignorance was such, but at the length, {repeat} {repeat} experience made me wonder, made me wonder, that harts and tongues, {repeat} did lodge so farre assunder. but at the length, {repeat} {repeat} experience made me wonder, made me wonder, that harts and tongues, {repeat} did lodge so farre assunder, that harts and tongues, did lodge so farre assunder, so farre assunder.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:39"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXI. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen first by force of fatall deste╌ny, from Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage towne the Troyan knyght did sayle, Queene Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do fayre, {repeat} with wofull wepyng eye, wepyng eye, his strange depart, {repeat} did greauously bewayle, did greauously bewaile: And when no sighes nor teares, could ease her smart, with sword full sharpe, {repeat} {repeat} she pearst, she pearst her tender hart, her tender hart. her tender hart: And when no &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:39"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXII. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thought that loue had beene a boy, that loue had beene a boy, with blinded eyes, or else some other wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton toy that men deuise, that men deuise, lyke tales of fayryes of╌ten told, by doting age that dyes, that dyes for cold, for cold, lyke tales of fayryes often told, by doting age that dyes for cold, that dyes for cold, by doting age that dyes for cold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:40"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXIII. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Deere life, O deere life, when may it be, when may it be, that mine eyes thine eyes may see, thine eyes may see, and in them, and in them my minde discouer, {repeat} whether absence hath had force, hath had force, thy remembrance to de╌force, from the Image of thy louer, from the Image of thy louer.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O, if I my selfe finde not,</l>
                        <l>though my parting ought forgot</l>
                        <l>Nor debard from beauties treasure</l>
                        <l>Let no tongue aspier to tell</l>
                        <l>In what hie Ioyes I shall dwell,</l>
                        <l>Onely thought aymes at the pleasure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thought therefore I will send thee</l>
                        <l>To take vp the place for me,</l>
                        <l>Long I will not after tary,</l>
                        <l>There vnseene thou maist be bold</l>
                        <l>These faire wonders to behold,</l>
                        <l>Which in them my hopes do cary.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:40"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXIIII. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oue, loue would discharge, loue would discharge, discharge, the dewty of his hart, in beauties praise, whose greatnes doth denye, wordes to his thougths, {repeat} and thoughts to her desart, to her de╌sart, which high conceyts, conceyts, since nothing can supply, supply Loue heere constraynd, through conquest to confesse, through conquest to confesse, byds silence sighe, byds silence sighe, that tongue cannot expresse, that tongue cannot ex╌presse. Loue heere &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:41"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXV. MEDIVS. A Carowle for Christmas day, the quire whereof (Reioyce) being of 4. parts, is the XXIIII. song.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> FRom Virgins wombe this day, this day dyd spring the pre╌tious seed▪ that onely saued man, this day let man reioyce and sweetly sing, since on this day our Sauiour first began. This day this day dyd Christ mans soule from death remoue, with glorious Saincts to dwell in heauen aboue. With glorious Saints to dwell in heauen a╌aboue, aboue.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>This day to man came pledge of perfect peace,</l>
                        <l>This day to man came loue and vnitie,</l>
                        <l>This day mans griefe began for to surcease,</l>
                        <l>This day dyd man receiue a remedie,</l>
                        <l>For each offence and euery deadly sinne,</l>
                        <l>With guiltie hart that earst he wandred in.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>In Christ his flock let loue be surely plast,</l>
                        <l>From Christ his flock let concord hate expell,</l>
                        <l>Of Christ his flock let loue be so embrast,</l>
                        <l>As we in Christ, and Christ in vs may dwell,</l>
                        <l>Christ is the Author of sweet vnitie,</l>
                        <l>From whence procedeth all felicitie.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O sing vnto this glittering glorious king,</l>
                        <l>O praise his name let euery liuing thing,</l>
                        <l>Let hart and voyce like bells of siluer ring,</l>
                        <l>The comfort that this day to man doth bring,</l>
                        <l>Let Lute, let Shalme, with sound of sweet delight,</l>
                        <l>These ioyes of Christ his birth this day resight.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:41"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. The first part, XXXVI. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F gold all burnisht, and brighter then sunne beames, were those curled lockes vpon her noble head, from whose deepe conceits, {repeat} my true deseruings flead, wherefore these mine eyes, {repeat} such store of teares out streames, such store of teares out streemes. Her eyes are faire starrs, her red like damaske rose, her white siluer shyne of Moone on Christall streames, her beauty perfect, {repeat} where on my fancies dreame, her lippes are rubies {repeat} her teeth of pearles two rowes. {repeat}</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="37" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:42"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. The second part. XXXVII. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> HEr breath is more sweet, is more sweet, more sweete then perfect Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is, her yeeres are in prime, and nothing doth she want, doth she want, &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doth she want, that might draw Angells from Heauen to further blisse, {repeat} from Heauen to further blisse, {repeat} of all things perfect, of all things perfect. This do I most complaine, her hart is a rock made all of Adamant, is a rock made all of Adamant, which guifts all delight, delight, {repeat} this last doth onely paine, this last doth onely paine, doth onely paine, this last doth onely paine, doth onely paine, {repeat} this last doth onely paine, onely paine.</p>
                     <trailer>¶ Heere endeth the songs of 5. parts.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="38" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:42"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XXXVIII. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold how good a thing it is, how good a thing it is, behold how good a thing it is, for bretheren to agree, to agree, when men amongst them do no stryfe, but peace and concord see, {repeat} full lyke vnto the pretious balme, the preti╌ous balme, {repeat} from Arons heed that fell, {repeat} from Arons hed that fell, that fell, and did descend, {repeat} vppon his beard, his garment skirts vntyll, vn╌tyll, his garment skyrts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="39" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:43"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XXXIX. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND as the pleasant morning dew, the pleasant morning, dew, the Mountaynes doth releeue {repeat} the Mountaines doth releeue: So God will blesse where concord is, where con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord is, so God will blesse where concord is, where concord is, and lyfe eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall giue. {repeat} {repeat} and lyfe eternall giue, eter╌nall giue, and life eternall giue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="40" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:43"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. XL. XLI. MEDIVS. A Carowle for Christmas day, the quire wherof (Cast of all doubtfull care) being of 4. parts, is the XXV. song.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> An earthly tree, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="41" type="song">
                     <head>Of 6. A Dialogue betwen two Sheperds. XLI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Who made the Hob, &amp;c. </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="42" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:44"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XLII. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND thinke ye Nimphes to scorne at loue, to scorne at loue, at loue, as if his fire were but of strawes, were but of strawes, he made the myghtye godds aboue, to stoope &amp; bowe vnto his myght, vnto his myght, &amp; with his shafts, his shafts of beau╌ty bright, he slayes the harts that scorne his might. And with his shafts, his shafts, and with his shafts, his shafts, of beau╌ty bryght, he slayes the harts that scorne his myght.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:44"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XLIII. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oue is a fitt of pleasure, loue is a fitt of pleasure, bred out of Idle braynes, out of Idle braynes, his fancies haue no measure, haue no mea╌sure, no more then haue his pains: his vayne affections lyke the wether, lyke the wether, precise or fond, we wot not whether, we wot not whether, we wot not whether, we wot not whether.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="44" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:45"/>
                     <head>Of 6 voc. XLIIII. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> IF in thine hart thou nourish will and giue all to thy lust, and giue all to thy lust, {repeat} to thy lust, then sorowes sharpe and griefes at length, endure of force thou must, {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} but if that reason rule thy will &amp; gouerne al thy minde, and gouerne all thy minde, {repeat} a blessed life then shalt thou leade, {repeat} a blessed life then shalt thou lead, and fewest daungers finde, and fewest daungers finde, {repeat} &amp; fewest daū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers finde, and fewest daungers finde. {repeat}</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="45" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:45"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. Psal. 121. XLV. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto the hills myne eyes I lyft, {repeat} my hope shall neuer fade, but from the Lord I looke for helpe, I looke for helpe, but from the Lord I looke for helpe, that Heauen and earth hath made, hath made, that Heauen and earth hath made. Thy foote he will from slipping saue, {repeat} and he that doth thee keepe, thee keepe, with watchfull eye will thee pre╌serue, will thee preserue, without flomber or sleepe, or sleepe, The Lord thy keeper and shade is, and standes at thy right arme, {repeat} the Sunne by day shall not thee burne, nor Moone by nyght thee harme, thee harme.
<pb facs="tcp:176435:46"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> The Lord shall keepe thee from all yll, shall keepe thee from all yll, thy soule he shall preserue, {repeat} he shall preserue, and all thy waies both in &amp; out, {repeat} for euer shall conserue, {repeat} shall conserue, for euer shall conserue, conserue, for euer shall conserue, {repeat} conserue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="46" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:46"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XLVI. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>C Christ rising againe &amp;c. Death from henceforth, {repeat} hath no power vppon him, to put away sinne to put away sinne. And so likewise count your selues dead, dead vnto sinne, but liueing vnto God, {repeat} In Christ Iesus our Lord, In Christ Iesus our Lord, Iesus our Lord.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="47" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:47"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XLVII. MEDIVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> CHrist is risen agayne &amp;c. Christ is risen againe, the first fruits of thē y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> sleepe, of them that sleepe, foreseing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> by man came death, that by man came death. for as by Adam, Adam, all mē do dye, all men do dye, do dye, so by Christ, so by Christ, by Christ, al mē shalbe restored to lyfe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored to life, to life, all mē shalbe restored to life, to life, restored to life, restored to lyfe, {repeat} {repeat} to life. Amen, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:47"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:48"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:48"/>
                  <p>CONTRATENOR.</p>
                  <p>¶ Songs of sundrie natures, some of grauitie, and others of myrth, fit for all compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and voyces. Lately made and composed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Musicke of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts: and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished for the delight of all such as take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in the exercise of that Art.</p>
                  <p>By VVilliam Byrd, one of the Gentlemen of the Queenes Maiesties honorable Chappell.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device (?) not found in McKerrow</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Thomas East, the assigne of William Byrd, and are to be sold at the house of the sayd T. East, being in Aldersgate streete, at the signe of the blacke Horse. 1589.</p>
                  <p>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:49"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:49"/>
                  <head>To the right honorable my very good Lord, Sir Henry Carye. Baron of Hunsdon, knight of the most noble order of the Garter, Lord Chamberlen to the Queenes most excelent Maiestie, Lord Warden of the East Marches towards Scotland, gouernor of Barwycke and the Castle of Norham, Captaine of the Gentlemen Pencioners, Iustice in Oyer, ouer all her Maiesties Forrests and Chases, on this side the Riuer of Trent, &amp; one of her Maiesties most honorable priuie councell▪ William Byrd wisheth increase of honor, with all true felicitie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing obserued (Right Honorable) that since the publishing in print, of my last labors in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, diuers persons of great honor and worship, haue more esteemed &amp; delighted in the exercise of that Art, then before. And being perswaded, that the same hath the rather encreased, through their good acceptation of my former endeuors: it hath especially moued and encouraged me to take further paines to gratifie theyr curteous dispositions therevnto, knowing that the varietie and choyse of songs, is both a prayse of the Art, and a pleasure to the delighted therein. And finding no person to whome the dedication thereof so fitly and properly belonged, as vnto your Lordship, by whome (through the honorable office which you exercise about her Maiesties person) both my selfe (for my place of seruice,) &amp; all other her highnesse Musitions are to be commanded, and vnder your high aucthoritie to be protected. And for many fauors to me shewed, being most deepely bound vnto your Honor, hauing not in me any other powre of seruiseable thanckfulnesse then in notes &amp; tunes of Musicke. I most humbly beseech your Lordship to take into your Honorable protection, these my poore trauells in that Art, accepting them as seruants redy to giue your L. delight, after you haue bene forewearied in affayres of great importance. Besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching almightie God to giue you a long, healthie, and happie lyfe, with a blessed end. I humbly take my leaue.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Lordships most bounden, William Byrd.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_courteous_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:50"/>
                  <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Inding that my last Impression of Musicke (most gentle Reader) through thy curtesie and fauor, hath had good passage and vtterance: and that since the publishing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the exercise and loue of that Art to haue exceedingly encreased. I haue bene encouraged thereby, to take fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paines therein, and to make thee pertaker thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I would shew my selfe gratefull to thee for thy loue, and desirous to delight thee with varietie, whereof (in my opinion) no Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is more plentifully adorned then Musicke. For which purpose I do now publish for thee, songs of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts, to serue for all companies and voyces: whereof some are easie and plaine to sing, other more hard and difi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, but all, such as any yong practicioner in singing, with a little foresight, may easely performe. If I finde thy curtesie to extend aswell to these my present trauells, as it hath done to my former endeuors, I will make my selfe endebted to thee during my lyfe, of whatsoeuer is in me, to yeeld thy delight in Musick, any satisfaction.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The most affectionate freend to all that loue or learne Musick William Byrd.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="countertenor" type="partbook">
                  <div n="15" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:50"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The first part. XV. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> IS loue a boy? {repeat} a boy, is loue a boy? what meanes he then to stryke, {repeat} or is he blynd, {repeat} why will he be a guyde, is he a man, why doth he hurt his lyke, {repeat} is he a God, {repeat} {repeat} why doth he men deryde, {repeat} {repeat} deryd, why doth he men deryde, {repeat} deryde, deryde. No one of these, {repeat} of these, no one of these but one compact of all, {repeat} a wilfull boy, {repeat} a man still dealyng blowes, of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to lead mē to their thral {repeat} a God y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> rules, {repeat} a God y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> rules, vnruly, God he knowes, {repeat} vnruly, God he knowes, he knowes, vnruly, God he knowes, {repeat} he knowes, God he knowes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:51"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The second part. XVI. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Oy pittye me that am a child againe, blynde be no more my guide to make me stray, my guide to make me stray, to make me stray, to make me stray, man vse thy might, {repeat} to force away, to force away my paine, {repeat} my paine, God do me good, {repeat} do me good, and leade me to my way, {repeat} to my way, and leade me to my way: And if thou beest a powre to me vn╌knowne, and if thou beest a powre to me vn╌knowne, vnknowne, powre of my life, let heere thy grace be showne, be showne, let heere thy grace be showne, thy grace be showne, let heere thy grace be showne. And if &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:51"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The first part. XVII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> WOunded I am and dare not seeke reliefe, wounded I am &amp; dare not seeke reliefe, for this new stroke vnseene but not vnfelt, vnseene but not vnfelt, but not vnfelt, no bloud nor bruise is witnes of my griefe, is witnes of my griefe, but sighes &amp; teares, {repeat} wherwith I mourne and melt, &amp; melt, wherwith I mourne &amp; melt, &amp; melt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I mourne and melt, &amp; melt, If I complaine, my witnes is suspect▪ If I complaine, my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is sus╌pect, if I containe, with cares I am vndone, with cares I am vndone, I am vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, sit still &amp; dye, tel truth and be reiect, tell truth and be re╌iect, O hatefull choyse, {repeat} that sorow cannot shun, cannot shun, that sorow cannot shun, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not shun, that sorow can not shun, cannot shun.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:52"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The second part. XVIII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Et of vs twaine whose losse shalbe the lesse, whose losse shal be the lesse, myne of my life, or you of your good name, light is my death regarding my distresse, my distresse, regarding my distresse, my dis╌tresse, my dis╌tresse, but your offence cryes out to your diffame, to your dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame, but your offence cryes out to your diffame, {repeat} A virgin fayre hath slayne for lacke of grace, {repeat} of grace, the man that made an Idoll of her face, {repeat} the man that made an Idoll of her face. A virgin. &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:52"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The first part. XIX. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom Citheron the warlyke boy is fled, is fled, &amp; smiling sits vppon a virgins lap, therby to traine poore misers to the trappe, whom beauty drawes with fancye to be fedde, to be fedde, with fancye to be feede, {repeat} and when desire, and when desire with eager lookes is ledde, then from her eyes, the arrow flyes, {repeat} fethered with flame, arm'd with a golden head, arm'd with a gol╌den head. {repeat}</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:53"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The second part. XX. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> THere carelesse thoughts are freed of that flame, wherwith her thrales are, wherewith her tharles are scorched to the hart, to the hart, if loue would so, {repeat} would God, th'enchauntyng dart, might once returne &amp; burne, from whence it came, {repeat} it came, from whence it came, {repeat} {repeat} not to deface, {repeat} of beautyes worke the frame, the frame, but by re╌bownd, it might be found, {repeat} what secret smart I suffer by the same. by the same, what secret smart I suffer by the same, by the same, what secret smart I suffer by the same, what secret smart I suffer by the same.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:53"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The third part. XXI. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> IF loue be iust, {repeat} then iust is my desire, and if vniust why is he calld a God, why is he calld a God, O God, O good, O iust, O iust, reserue thy rod, reserue thy rod to chasten those that from thy lawes retyre, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre, that from thy lawes re╌tyre, but chuse a ryght {repeat} good loue, good, loue I thee de╌sire, the golden head, golden head, not that of lead, of lead, not that of lead. of lead, her hart is frost, and must dissolue by fyre. her hart is frost, is frost, her hart is frost, and must dis╌solue by fire, and must dissolue by fire, {repeat} by fire, and must dissolue by fire.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:54"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord my God, let flesh &amp; bloud thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant not subdew, thy seruant not sub╌dew, {repeat} O Lord my God, let flesh and bloud thy seruant not subdew, sub╌dew, nor let the world deceiue me, the world deceiue me, with his glory most vnture, let not O Lord, {repeat} O myghty God, let not thy mortall foe, thy mor╌tall foe, let not the feend with all his craft, with all his craft, with all his craft, thy seruant, thy seruant ouerthrow: But to re╌sist, giue fortitude, but to resist, giue patience to endure, to endure,
<pb facs="tcp:176435:54"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> giue constency that alwaies thine, that alwaies thine, I may perseuer sure, {repeat} I may perse╌uer sure, per╌seuer sure, I may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seuer sure, perseuer sure, perseuer sure.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:55"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXIII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hyle that the Sunne with his beames hot, scorched the fruits in vale &amp; moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, moūtaine: Philon the sheperd late forgot, sitting besides a Christall fountaine, sitting besides besides a Christall fountaine, in shadow of a greene Oke tree, vppon his pipe, {repeat} this song playd he, this song playd he: adew loue, adew loue, vntrue loue, vntrue loue, vntrue loue, adew loue, adew loue, your minde is light, {repeat} soone lost, soone lost
<pb facs="tcp:176435:55"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> for new loue, soone lost for new loue, for new loue, soone lost for new loue.</p>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <head>2</head>
                        <l>So long as I was in your sight,</l>
                        <l>I was as your hart, your soule, your treasure,</l>
                        <l>And euermore you sob'd, you sigh'd,</l>
                        <l>Burning in flames beyond all measure,</l>
                        <l>Three dayes endur'd your Loue to me,</l>
                        <l>And it was lost in other three.</l>
                        <l>Adew Loue adew loue vntrue loue,</l>
                        <l>Vntrue loue vntrue loue adew loue,</l>
                        <l>Your mynd is light, soone lost for new loue</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <head>3</head>
                        <l>Another shepherd you dyd see,</l>
                        <l>To whome your hart was soone enchayned,</l>
                        <l>Full soone your loue was leapt from me,</l>
                        <l>Full soone my place he had obtayned,</l>
                        <l>Soone came a third your loue to winne,</l>
                        <l>And we were out and he was in.</l>
                        <l>Adew loue, &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="4">
                        <head>4</head>
                        <l>Sure you haue made me passing glad,</l>
                        <l>That you your mynd so soone remoued,</l>
                        <l>Before that I the leysure had,</l>
                        <l>To chuse you for my best beloued.</l>
                        <l>For all my loue was past and doonne,</l>
                        <l>Two dayes before it was begoonne.</l>
                        <l>Adew Loue &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:56"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXIIII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eioyce, reioyce, with hart and voyce, with hart and voyce, with hart and voice in Christ his byrth this day, this day reioyce, reioyce, in Christ his birth this day, this day, reioyce, reioyce, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, reioyce, reioyce, reioyce, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, reioyce, reioyce.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:56"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXV. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ast of all doubtfull care, all doubtfull care, cast of all doubtfull care, exile and banish teares, to ioyfull newes deuine, {repeat} to ioyfull newes deuine, deuine, lend vs your listning eares▪ your listning eares, lend vs your listning eares, lend vs your listning eares, lend vs your listning eares.</p>
                     <trailer>¶ <hi>Heere endeth the songs of foure parts.</hi>
                     </trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:57"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVI. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Eping full sore, full sore, weping full sore, with face as fayre as siluer, {repeat} not wanting rose nor lilly white to paint it, nor lilly white to paint it, I saw a lady walke, fast by, fast by a riuer, I saw a lady walke fast by a riuer, vppon whose bankes Dianaes Nimphes all dawn╌ced, {repeat} Dianaes Nimphes all dawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, {repeat} her beauty great, {repeat} {repeat} had diuers gods inchaunted, {repeat} among the which loue was the first transformed, loue was the first trans╌formed, who vnto her his bow, his bow and shafts had graunted, who vnto her his bow and shafts had graunted, and by her sight,
<pb facs="tcp:176435:57"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> to adamant was tur╌ned. {repeat} to adamant was turned, {repeat} Alas quoth I, alas quoth I, what meaneth, what meaneth this demeanure, {repeat} so faire a dame to be so full of so╌rowe, so full of sorow: No wonder quoth a Nimphe, she wanteth, she wanteth plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, her teares and sighes, {repeat} ne ceasse from eaue to morow, ne ceasse from eaue to mor╌row. This lady Rich is Rich is of the gifts of beauty, rich is of the gifts of bewtye, but vnto her, {repeat} are gifts of fortune daynty. {repeat} are gifts of fortune daynty. This lady &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:58"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Enelope: That longed for the sight, Penelo╌pe that longed for the sight, for the sight of her Vlisses, wandring, wandering all to long, felt neuer ioy wherein she tooke delyght, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in she tooke de╌lyght, although she liu'd in greatest ioyes among, so I poore wretch, possessing that, possessing that I craue, both liue and lacke, and lacke, by wrong of that I haue: Then blame me not, {repeat} although to heauens, although to heauens I crye, I crye, and pray the gods, that shortly I might dye, that shortly I might dye, that I myght dye: Then blame me not, {repeat} although to heauens, although to heauens I cry, I cry, and pray the gods,
<pb facs="tcp:176435:58"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> that shortly I might, that shortly I might dye, that I might dye, that I might dye, that I myght dye, {repeat} that I myght dye.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:59"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVIII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ompell the Hauke to sit that is vnmand, compell the Hawke to sit that is vnmand, that is vn╌mand, or make the Hound vn╌taught, to draw the Deere, {repeat} to draw the Deere, or bring the free against his will in band, in band, against his will in band, or moue the sad a pleasant tale to heare, a pleasant tale to heare, a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant tale to heare, your tyme is lost, and you are neare the neere, {repeat} and you are neare the neere, your time is lost, and you are neare the neere, {repeat} So Loue, ne learnes by force the knot to knit, to knit, the knot to
<pb facs="tcp:176435:59"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> knit, he serues but those that feele sweete fancies fitt, he serues but those that feele, he serues but those that feele sweet fancies fitt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:60"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXIX. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ee those sweet eyes, see, see those sweete eyes, those sweet eyes, those more then sweetest eyes, eyes, whom the starres, the starres exceede, the starres exceede not in their place. See Loue at gaze, at gaze, See Loue at gaze, at gaze, Loue that would faine deuise, Loue that would faine deuise, but cannot speake, to plead his wondrous case.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:60"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXX. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I was otherwise then now I am, then now I am, I loued more but skylled not so much, fayre wordes and smyles could haue contented than, could haue contented than, my simple age &amp; ignorance was such, and ignorance was such: But at the length, {repeat} experience made me wonder, {repeat} that harts and tongues, {repeat} did lodge so farre assunder, but at the length, the length, but at the length, {repeat} experience, experience made me wonder, that harts and tongues did lodge, did lodge so farre a sunder, that harts and tongues did lodge so farre assunder, so farre assunder.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:61"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXI. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VHen first by force of fatall desteny, from Carthage towne the Troyan knyght, the Troyan knight did sayle, Queene Dido fayre, with wofull wepyng eye, with wofull wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng eye, his strange depart, {repeat} did greauously be╌wayle: And when no sighes nor teares, nor teares, could ease, could ease her smart, with sword full sharpe, full sharpe, with sword full sharpe, {repeat} she pearst, she pearst her tender hart. And when no &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:61"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thought that loue had beene a boy, {repeat} with blynded eyes, or else some other wanton toy that men deuise, that men deuise, {repeat} like tales of fayryes often told, by doting age that dyes for cold▪ for cold, for cold, that dyes for cold, lyke tales of fayryes of╌ten told, by doting age that dyes for cold, by doting age that dyes for cold, for cold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:62"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXIII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Deere life when may it be, when may it be, when may it be, that mine eyes thine eyes may see, and in them my minde discouer, {repeat} whether absence hath had force, thy remembrance to deforce, from the Image of thy lou╌er, from the Image of thy louer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:62"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXIIII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oue would dis╌charge, {repeat} discharge, the dewty of his hart, in beauties prayse whose greatnesse doth de╌nye, whose greatnesse doth deny, wordes to his thoughts, his thoughts, wordes to his thoughts, his thoughts, and thoughts to her desart, and thoughts to her de╌sart, which hygh conceits, since nothing can supply: Loue heere constrayned through conquest to confesse, loue heere constrayned through conquest to confesse, byds silence sighe, silence sighe that tongue cannot expresse, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse. Loue heere &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:63"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXV. CONTRATENOR. A Carowle for Christmas day, the quire whereof (Reioyce) being of 4. parts, is the XXIIII. song.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> FRom Virgins wombe, &amp;c. </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>FRom Virgins wombe this day did spring,</l>
                        <l>The precious seed that saued man,</l>
                        <l>This day let man reioyce and sweetly sing</l>
                        <l>Since on this day saluacion first began,</l>
                        <l>This day dyd Christ mans soule from death remoue</l>
                        <l>With glorious Saints to dwell in heauen aboue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>This day to man came pledge of perfect peace,</l>
                        <l>This day to man came loue and vnitie,</l>
                        <l>This day mans griefe began for to surcease,</l>
                        <l>This day dyd man receiue a remedie,</l>
                        <l>For each offence and euery deadly sinne,</l>
                        <l>With guiltie hart that earst he wandred in.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>In Christ his flock let loue be surely plast,</l>
                        <l>From Christ his flock let concord hate expell,</l>
                        <l>Of Christ his flock let loue be so embrast,</l>
                        <l>As we in Christ, and Christ in vs may dwell,</l>
                        <l>Christ is the Author of sweet vnitie,</l>
                        <l>From whence procedeth all felicitie.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O sing vnto this glittering glorious king,</l>
                        <l>O praise his name let euery liuing thing,</l>
                        <l>Let hart and voyce like bells of siluer ring,</l>
                        <l>The comfort that this day to man doth bring,</l>
                        <l>Let Lute, let Shalme, with sound of sweet delight▪</l>
                        <l>These ioyes of Christ his birth this day resight.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:63"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. The first part. XXXVI. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F gold all burnisht, and brighter then sunne beames, then sunne beames, were those curled lockes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon her noble head, from whose deepe conceits, {repeat} my true deseruings flead, wherfore these mine eyes, such store of teares out streames, out streames, such store of teares out streames. Her eyes are faire starrs, her red like damaske rose, damask: rose, her white siluer shyne of Moone, of Moone, on Christall streame, her beauty perfect, {repeat} wheron my fancies dreame, her lips are rubies, {repeat} her teeth of pearle two rowes, her teeth of pearle, of pearle two rowes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="37" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:64"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. The second part. XXXVII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> HEr breath is more sweet then perfect Amber is, Amber is, her yeeres are in prime &amp; nothing doth she want, doth she want, {repeat} that might draw Angells from Heauen, that might draw Angells frō Heauen, {repeat} to further blisse, {repeat} to further blisse: of all things perfect this do I most complaine, most complaine, her hart is a rocke, made all of Adamant, is a rock made all of Adamant, which guifts all delight, {repeat} delight, which guifts all delight, this last doth onely paine, doth onely paine, this last doth onely paine, {repeat} onely paine, this last doth onely paine.</p>
                     <trailer>Heere endeth the songs of 5. parts.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="38" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:64"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XXXVIII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold how good a thing it is, it is, behold how good a thing it is, for brethren to agree, {repeat} to agree, when men amongst them do no stryfe, but peace and concord, but peace and concord see, and concord see, full like vnto, full like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pretious balme, from Arons head that fell, from Arons head that fell, that fell, and did descend, and did descend vppon his beard, his garment skyrts vn╌tyll, his garment skyrts vntyll, {repeat} his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment skyrts vntyll.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="39" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:65"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XXXIX. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND as the pleasant morning dew, morning dew, the Mountaynes doth re╌leeue, doth re╌leeue, the Mountaines doth re╌leeue, doth releeue, so God wil blesse wher concord is, {repeat} so God wil blesse wher concord is, {repeat} and lyfe eternall giue. eternall giue, and lyfe eternall giue, {repeat} eter╌nall giue, and life eternall giue, and lyfe eternall giue, eter╌nall giue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="40" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:65"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. XL. CONTRATENOR. A Carowle for Christmas day, the quire whereof (Cast of all doubtfull care) being of 4. parts, is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> XXV. song.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> An earthly tree. </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>AN earthly tree a heauenly fruit it bare,</l>
                        <l>A case of clay containd a crowne immortall,</l>
                        <l>A crowne of crownes, a king whose cost &amp; care</l>
                        <l>Redeemd poore man, whose race before was thrall</l>
                        <l>To death, to dome, to paines of euerlasting,</l>
                        <l>By his sweet death, skornes, strypes; &amp; often fasting.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Starre aboue the Starres, a Sonne of light,</l>
                        <l>Whose blessed beames this wretched earth bespred</l>
                        <l>With hope of Heauen and of Gods sonne the sight</l>
                        <l>Which in our flesh and sinfull soule lay dead,</l>
                        <l>O fayth, O hope, O ioyes renownd for euer,</l>
                        <l>O liuely lyfe that deathlesse shall perseuer.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then let vs sing the Iullabyes of sleepe,</l>
                        <l>To this sweet babe, borne to awake vs all,</l>
                        <l>From drowsie sinne that made old Adam weepe,</l>
                        <l>And by his fault gaue to mankinde the fall,</l>
                        <l>For loe this day, the byrth day, day of dayes,</l>
                        <l>Somons our songs to giue him laud &amp; praise.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="41" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:66"/>
                     <head>Of 6. A Dialogue betwen two Sheperds. XLI. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> WHo made thee Hob, &amp;c. </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="42" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:66"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XLII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND think ye Nymphes to scorne at Loue, {repeat} as if his fire were but of strawes, he made the mightie Gods aboue to stoope and bow vnto his lawes, &amp; with his shaft of beautie bright, of beautie bright, he slayes the harts, he slayes the harts that scorne his might. And with his shaft of beautie bright, of beautie bright, he slayes the harts, he slaies the harts that scorne his might.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:67"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XLIII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oue is a fitt of pleasure, of pleasure, bred out of Idle braynes, his fancies haue no measure, no measure, no more then haue his pains: his vayne affections lyke the we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, lyke the we╌ther, precise or fond, or fond, we wot not whether, we wot not whether.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="44" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:67"/>
                     <head>Of 6 voc. XLIIII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> IF in thine hart thou nourish will and giue all to thy lust, {repeat} then sorowes sharpe and griefes at length, {repeat} endure of force thou must, {repeat} {repeat} but if that reason rule thy will &amp; gouerne al thy minde, {repeat} a blessed life then shalt thou leade, and fewest daungers finde, a blessed life then shalt thou lead, and fewest daungers finde, and fewest daungers finde, daun╌gers finde, and fewest daungers finde, fewest daungers finde, {repeat} {repeat} and fewest daungers finde, daun╌gers finde.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="45" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:68"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. Psal. 121. XLV. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto the hills myne eyes I lyft, myne eyes I lyft, my hope shall neuer fade, {repeat} but from the Lord I looke for helpe, I looke for helpe, that Heauen and earth hath made, {repeat} that Heauen and earth hath made. Thy foote he will from slipping saue, and he that doth thee keepe, that doth thee keepe, with watchfull eye will thee preserue, will thee preserue, without slomber or sleepe, {repeat} {repeat} The Lord the keeper and shade is, and stands at thy right arme, {repeat} the Sunne by day shall not thee burne, nor Moone by nyght thee harme, thee harme,
<pb facs="tcp:176435:68"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> The Lord shall keepe thee from all yll, thy soule he shall preserue {repeat} {repeat} and all thy waies both in and out, and out, and all thy wayes both in and out, for euer shall conserue. shall conserue, for euer shall con╌serue, {repeat} {repeat} for euer shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue, shall con╌serue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="46" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:69"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XLVI. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> CHrist rising. Death from henceforth, Death from henceforth hath no power vppon him, to pur away sinne, to put away sinne, And so likewise count your selues dead vnto sinne, but lyuing vnto God, but lyuing vn╌to God, In Christ Iesus our Lord, our Lord, Iesus our Lord. </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="47" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:69"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XLVII. CONTRATENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> CHrist is risen againe, &amp;c. Christ is risen againe, the first fruits of thē that sleep, that sleep, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first fruits of thē y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> sleepe, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> sleepe. foreseeing, foreseeing, that by man came death, For as by Adam, Adam, all men do dye, {repeat} do dye. So by Christ, euen so by Christ, by Christ, by Christ, all men shalbe restored to lyfe, all men shalbe restored to lyfe, restored to lyfe, to lyfe, restored to lyfe, {repeat} restored
<pb facs="tcp:176435:69"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> to lyfe, to lyfe, to lyfe, to lyfe. A╌men, A╌men,</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:70"/>
                  <head>¶ <hi>A Table of all the songs contained in these Bookes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 3. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>LOrd in thy rage. I</item>
                        <item>Right blest are they. II</item>
                        <item>Lord in thy wrath. III</item>
                        <item>O God which art most mercifull. IIII</item>
                        <item>Lord heare my prayer instantly. V</item>
                        <item>From depth of sinne O Lord. VI</item>
                        <item>Attend myne humble prayer Lord. VII</item>
                        <item>Susanna fayre. VIII</item>
                        <item>The Nightingale. IX</item>
                        <item>When yonglings first. 1. part. X</item>
                        <item>But when by proofe. 2 part. XI</item>
                        <item>Vppon a sommers day. 1 part. XII</item>
                        <item>Then for a bote. 2 part. XIII</item>
                        <item>The greedy Hauke. XIIII</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 4. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>IS Loue a boy. 1 part. XV</item>
                        <item>Boy pittie mee. 2 part. XVI</item>
                        <item>Wounded I am. 1 part. XVII</item>
                        <item>Yet of vs twaine. 2 part. XVIII</item>
                        <item>From Citheron. 1 part. XIX</item>
                        <item>There carelesse thoughts 2 part. XX</item>
                        <item>If Loue be iust. 3 part. XXI</item>
                        <item>O Lord my God. XXII</item>
                        <item>While that the Sunne. XXIII</item>
                        <item>Reioyce, reioyce. XXIIII</item>
                        <item>Cast of all doubtfull care. XXV</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 5. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>WEeping full sore. XXVI</item>
                        <item>Penelope. XXVII</item>
                        <item>Compell y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Hauke to sit. XXVIII</item>
                        <item>See, see those sweet eyes. XXIX</item>
                        <item>When I was otherwise then now▪ I am. XXX</item>
                        <item>When first by force. XXXI</item>
                        <item>I thought that loue had bene a boy. XXXII</item>
                        <item>O deere lyfe when may it be. XXXIII</item>
                        <item>Loue would discharge. XXXIIII</item>
                        <item>From Virgins wombe. XXXV</item>
                        <item>Of gold all burnisht. 1. part. XXXVI</item>
                        <item>Her breath is more sweet. 2. part. XXXVII</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 6. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>BEhold how good a thing it is. 1 part. XXXVIII</item>
                        <item>And as the pleasant morning dew. 2 part. XXXIX</item>
                        <item>An earthly tree. XL</item>
                        <item>Who made thee Hob. XLI</item>
                        <item>And think ye Nymphes. 1. part. XLII</item>
                        <item>Loue is a fit of pleasure. 2. part. XLIII</item>
                        <item>If in thine hart. XLIIII</item>
                        <item>Vnto the hills. XLV</item>
                        <item>Christ rising againe. 1 part. XLVI</item>
                        <item>Christ is risen againe. 2. part. XLVII</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London by Thomas East, dwelling in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dersgate streete, at the signe of the blacke Horse.</hi> 1589.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:70"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:71"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:71"/>
                  <p>TENOR.</p>
                  <p>¶ Songs of sundrie natures, some of grauitie, and others of myrth, fit for all compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and voyces. Lately made and composed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Musicke of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts: and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished for the delight of all such as take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in the exercise of that Art.</p>
                  <p>By VVilliam Byrd, one of the Gentlemen of the Queenes Maiesties honorable Chappell.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device (?) not found in McKerrow</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Thomas East, the assigne of William Byrd, and are to be sold at the house of the sayd T. East, being in Aldersgate streete, at the signe of the blacke Horse. 1589.</p>
                  <p>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:72"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:72"/>
                  <head>To the right honorable my very good Lord, Sir Henry Carye, Baron of Hunsdon, knight of the most noble order of the Garter, Lord Chamberlen to the Queenes most excelent Maiestie, Lord Warden of the East Marches towards Scotland, gouernor of Barwycke and the Castle of Norham, Captaine of the Gentlemen Pencioners, Iustice in Oyer, ouer all her Maiesties Forrests and Chases, on this side the Riuer of Trent, &amp; one of her Maiesties most honorable priuie councell. William Byrd wisheth increase of honor, with all true felicitie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing obserued (Right Honorable) that since the publishing in print, of my last labors in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, diuers persons of great honor and worship, haue more esteemed &amp; delighted in the exercise of that Art, then before. And being perswaded, that the same hath the rather encreased, through their good acceptation of my former endeuors: it hath especially moued and encouraged me to take further paines to gratifie theyr curteous dispositions therevnto, knowing that the varietie and choyse of songs, is both a prayse of the Art, and a pleasure to the delighted therein. And finding no person to whome the dedication thereof so fitly and properly belonged, as vnto your Lordship, by whome (through the honorable office which you exercise about her Maiesties person) both my selfe (for my place of seruice,) &amp; all other her highnesse Musitions are to be commanded, and vnder your high aucthoritie to be protected. And for many fauors to me shewed, being most deepely bound vnto your Honor, hauing not in me any other powre of seruiseable thanckfulnesse then in notes &amp; tunes of Musicke. I most humbly beseech your Lordship to take into your Honorable protection, these my poore trauells in that Art, accepting them as seruants redy to giue your L. delight, after you haue bene forewearied in affayres of great importance. Besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching almightie God to giue you a long, healthie, and happie lyfe, with a blessed end. I humbly take my leaue.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Lordships most bounden, William Byrd.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_courteous_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:73"/>
                  <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Inding that my last Impression of Musicke (most gentle Reader) through thy curtesie and fauor, hath had good passage and vtterance: and that since the publishing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the exercise and loue of that Art to haue exceedingly encreased. I haue bene encouraged thereby, to take fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paines therein, and to make thee pertaker thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I would shew my selfe gratefull to thee for thy loue, and desirous to delight thee with varietie, whereof (in my opinion) no Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is more plentifully adorned then Musicke. For which purpose I do now publish for thee, songs of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts, to serue for all companies and voyces: whereof some are easie and plaine to sing, other more hard and difi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, but all, such as any yong practicioner in singing, with a little foresight, may easely performe. If I finde thy curtesie to extend aswell to these my present trauells, as it hath done to my former endeuors, I will make my selfe endebted to thee during my lyfe, of whatsoeuer is in me, to yeeld thy delight in Musick, any satisfaction.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The most affectionate freend to all that loue or learne Musick William Byrd.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="tenor" type="partbook">
                  <div n="1" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:73"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Domine in furore.</hi> Psal. 6. 1. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord in thy rage rebuke me not, for my most gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous sinne, most greeuous, most greeuous sinne, nor in thine anger chasten me, but let me fa╌uour winne, fauour winne, but let me fa╌uour winne, haue mercy Lord on me, {repeat} on me, because my state is weake to see, to see, because my state is weake to see, heale me, O Lord, O Lord, heale me O Lord, for that my bones, {repeat} are troubled sore in me, {repeat} are troubled sore in me, in me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:74"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Beati quorum.</hi> Psal. 32. II. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight blest are they whose wicked sinnes, whose wicked sinnes, by God remitted be, by God remit╌ted be, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted be, and whose defaults are couered, are couered, through his great clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, {repeat} The man is blest, is blest, the man is blest, {repeat} to whom our Lord hath not imputed sinne, imputed sinne, hath not imputed sinne, {repeat} nor in his sprite, nor in his prite, deceyt is found, deceyt is found, nor takes delight there in, {repeat} nor takes delight there in, there in, nor takes delyght therein, {repeat} </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:74"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Domine ne.</hi> Psal. 38. III. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord in thy wrath, {repeat} correct me not, {repeat} nor in thy fury vexe, giue teares, {repeat} giue grace, giue penitence vnto my sinfull sexe, {repeat} for that the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of thy wrath are fixed in my hart, in my hart, are fixed in my hart, And thou hast layd thine hand one me, {repeat} on me, for my most iust deseart. de╌seart, for my most iust de╌seart.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:75"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Miserere mei Deus.</hi> Psal. 51. IIII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God which art most mercyfull, haue mercy Lord on me, {repeat} haue mercy Lord on me, according to thy mer╌cy great, let me releaued be, {repeat} let me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaued be. And put away my wickednes, {repeat} my wickednes, my wicked╌nes, And put away my wicked╌nes, which sundry wayes hath bene, hath beene, {repeat} according to the multitude, {repeat} of thy compassions seene. {repeat} according to the multitude of thy compassions seene, {repeat} of thy compassi╌ons seene.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:75"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Domine exaudi.</hi> Psal. 102. V. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord heare my prayer instantly, which I before thee make, before thee make, and let my cry come vnto thee, {repeat} do not the same forsake, {repeat} forsake. Turne not away thy face from me, when troubles me op╌presse, oppresse, each day in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline thine eare to me, incline thine eare to me, and suc╌cour my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tresse, {repeat} and suc╌cour my distresse. {repeat}</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:76"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>De profundis</hi> Psal. 130. VI. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom depth of sinne, {repeat} O Lord to thee, O Lord to thee, to thee, I haue made him╌ble cry, {repeat} Lord heare my voice, make it ascend, vnto thy throne so hye, vnto the voice of my request, pour'd out before thy sight, {repeat} Lord let thine eares attentiue be, to heare me day and night, day &amp; night, to heare me day and night, {repeat} day and night.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:76"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Domine exaudi.</hi> Psal. 143. VII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ttend mine humble prayer Lord, mine humble prayer Lord, attend, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend mine humble prayer Lord, with thine attentiue eare, attentiue eare, euen in thy truth and iustyce Lord, vouchsafe my sure to heare, {repeat} to heare. And into iudgement enter not, {repeat} with thy poore seruant heere, {repeat} {repeat} poore seruant heere, because none shalbe iustified, &amp; stād before thee cleere, before thee cleere, {repeat} because none shalbe iustifi'd, &amp; stand before thee cleere, before thee cleere, because none shalbe iustifi'd, and stand before thee cleere, before thee cleere, &amp; stand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee cleere, {repeat}</p>
                     <trailer>Heere endeth the seauen Psalmes.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:77"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. VIII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vsanna fayre, sometime assaulted was, by two old men, desiring their de╌light, which leude intent, {repeat} which leude intent they thought to bring to passe, if not by tender loue, {repeat} by force and might, to whom she said, If I your sute denye, your sute de╌ny, you will me falsely accuse, and make me dye, me dye, and make me dye, make me dye. And if I graunt to that which you request, my chastitye shall then defloured be, my chastitye shall then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>floured be, defloured be, which is so deere to me, to me, as I detest, my life,
<pb facs="tcp:176435:77"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> my life, if it berefted be from me, from me, and rather would I dye, {repeat} of mine accord, of myne accord, ten thousand tymes, {repeat} ten thousand times, then once offend our Lord, then once offend our Lord.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:78"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. IX. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Nightingale so pea╌sant and so gay, and so gay, so plea╌sant and so gay, and so gay, in greenewood groues, delights to make his dwelling, {repeat} in fields to flye, to flye, in fields to flye, to flye, chanting his roun╌delaye, his rounde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laye, at lyberty, at lybertye against the Cage rebelling, against the Cage re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel╌ling. But my poore hart, but my poore hart, but my poore hart with sorowes ouerswelling, through bondage vyle, bynding my freedome short, bynding my freedome short, bynding my freedome short, no plea╌sure takes, in these his
<pb facs="tcp:176435:78"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> sports excelling, in these his sports excel╌ling, in these his sports excelling, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling, nor in his song receyueth no comfort, nor in his song receiueth, nor in his song receiueth, nor in his song receiueth no com╌fort.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:79"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. The first part. X. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen younglyngs first on Cupide fyxe their sight, their sight, and see him naked, blyndfold &amp; a boy, &amp; a boy, though bow &amp; shafts and fier╌brand be his might, be his might, yet weene they he can worke them none annoy, {repeat} yet weene they he can worke them none an╌noy. And therefore with his purpill wings they play, for glorious semeth loue though light as fether, and when they haue done they weene to skape a╌way, for blynd men say they, say they, for &amp;c. shoote they know not whether. {repeat} shoote they know not whether, {repeat} shoote they know not whether.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:79"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. The second part. XI. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt when by proofe they finde that he did see, {repeat} &amp; that his wound did rather, did ra╌ther dym their sight, they wonder more how such a lad as he, should be of such surpassing powre &amp; myght: {repeat} should be of such surpassing powre and might, and might: but Ants haue gals, {repeat} so hath the Bee his styng, {repeat} his sting, then sheeld me heauens from such a subtyle thing, a subtyle thing, then sheeld me heauens from such a subtyle thing, from such a subtyle thing: then sheeld me heauens from such a sub╌tyle thing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:80"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. The first part. XII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ppon a Sommers day loue went to swym, and cast himselfe into a Sea of teares, {repeat} the clouds cald in their light, &amp; heauē waxt dym, {repeat} &amp; sighes did raise a tempest, and sighes did raise a tempest causing feares, a tempest causing feares. The naked boy, {repeat} could not so wyld his armes, but that the waues were maisters of his might, of his might, &amp; threatned him to worke farre greater harmes, {repeat} if he deuysed not to skape by flyght. {repeat} to skape by flyght.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:80"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. The second part. XIII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hen for a bote his quiuer stoode in stead, his quiuer stoode in steade, his bow vnbent did serue him for a mast, whereby to sayle his cloth of vayle he spread, {repeat} his cloth of vayle he spread, he spread, his shafts for ores on either bord he cast, {repeat} his shafts for ores on either bord he cast, he cast, from shypwracke safe this wag got thus to shore, {repeat} and sware, and sware, to bath in louers teares no more, in louers teares no more, to bath in louers teares no more.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:81"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. XIIII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He greedy Hawke, {repeat} with sooden sight of lure, with sooden sight, with sooden sight of lure, doth stoope, doth stoope in hope to haue, in hope to haue her wished pray, so many men do stoope, to sights vn╌sure, so many men do stoope, to sights vnsure, {repeat} and courteous speach, doth keepe them at the bay, {repeat} let them beware, {repeat} least frendly lookes be lyke, let them beware least frendly lookes be like the lure, whereat the so╌ring Hawke did strike▪ {repeat} whereat the so╌ryng Hawke did strike, the so╌ring Hawke did strike.</p>
                     <trailer>Here endeth the songs of three parts.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:81"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The first part. XV. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> IS loue a boy? {repeat} a boy, is loue a boy? what meanes he then to strike, {repeat} or is he blynde? {repeat} why will he be a guide, is he a man? why doth he hurt his like, {repeat} is he a God? {repeat} a God, why doth he men de╌ryde, {repeat} de╌ryde, why doth &amp;c. de╌ryde, de╌ryde: No one of these, {repeat} of these, no one of these, but one com╌pact of all, {repeat} a wilful boy, {repeat} a man stil dealing blowes, of purpose blynde, to leade men to their thral, {repeat} a God y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> rules, {repeat} y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> rules, vnruly, God he knowes, {repeat} God he knowes, vnruly, God he knowes, God he knowes. {repeat}</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:82"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The second part. XVI. TENOR. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Oy pittye me that am a child againe, that am a child a╌gaine, blynde be no more my guide to make me stray, to make me stray, blynde be no more to make me stray, my guide to make me stray, to make me stray, man vse thy might, {repeat} to force away my paine, {repeat} my paine, God do me good, {repeat} {repeat} and leade me to my way, {repeat} {repeat} to my way: And if thou beest a powre to me vn╌knowne, {repeat} a powre to me vn╌knowne, powre of my life, let heere thy grace be showne. {repeat} let heere thy grace be showne. And if &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:82"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The first part. XVII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ounded I am, and dare not seeke reliefe, wounded I am and dare not seeke reliefe, for this new stroke vnseene, for this new stroke vnseene, but not vnfelt, vnfelt, no bloud nor bruise is witnes to my greife, but sighes, and teares, {repeat} wherewith I mourne and melt, wherwith I mourne, wherewith I mourne and melt, if I complaine, my witnes is suspect, if I cōplaine my witnes is suspect, if I cōtaine, {repeat} if I cōtaine with cares I am vndone, vndone, sit stil &amp; dye, tell truth &amp; be reiect, O hatefull choyse, {repeat} that sorow cannot shun. {repeat} that sorow cannot shun.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:83"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The second part. XVIII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Et of vs twaine whose losse shalbe the lesse, whose losse shal╌be the lesse, myne of my life, or you of your good name, light is my death regarding my distresse, regarding my distresse, {repeat} but your offence cryes out to your diffame, {repeat} cryes out to your diffame, to your diffame: A virgin fayre hath slayne for lacke of grace, {repeat} of grace, the man that made an Idoll of her face, {repeat} the man that made an Idoll of her face, an Idoll of her face. A virgin. &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:83"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The first part. XIX. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom Citheron the warlyke boy is fled, the warlike boy is fled, and smilyng sits vppon a virgins lappe, therby to trayne poore misers to the trappe, whom beauty drawes with fancye to be fedde, {repeat} with fancye to be fedde, and when desire with eager lookes is ledde, {repeat} then from her eyes, the arrow flyes, {repeat} fethered with flame, arm'd with a golden head, arm'd with a gol╌den head.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:84"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The second part. XX. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here carelesse thoughts are freed of that flame, wher╌with her thrales are scorched to the hart, are scorched to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hart, if loue would so, {repeat} would God, th'enchaū╌tyng dart, might once returne &amp; burne, &amp; burne, might once returne &amp; burne, from whence it came, {repeat} returne, from whence it came, it came, not to deface, {repeat} of beautyes worke the frame, the frame, but by re╌bownd, it might be found, what secret smart I suffer, I suffer by the same. what secret smart, I suffer by the same, {repeat} I suf╌fer by the same.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:84"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The third part. XXI. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> IF loue be iust, {repeat} then iust is my desire, and if vniust, why is he calld a God, why is he calld a God, a God, O God, O God, O iust, O iust, reserue thy rod, {repeat} to chasten those that from thy lawes retyre, retyre, that from thy lawes retyre, but chuse aright, {repeat} good loue I thee require, the golden head, not that of lead, {repeat} her hart is frost and must dissolue, and must dis╌solue by fire, her hart is frost and must dissolue by fire▪ by fire, her hart is frost and must dissolue by fire, and must dissolue by fire, {repeat} by fire.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:85"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord my God, let flesh &amp; bloud thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant not subdew, let flesh and bloud thy seruant not subdew, O Lord my God, let flesh and bloud thy seruant not subdew, nor let the world deceiue me, {repeat} with his glory most vntrue, most vntrue, let not O Lord, O myghty God, let not, let not thy mortall foe, let not the feend with all his craft, his craft, let not the feend with all his craft, thy seruant ouerthrow: But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist, giue fortitude, but to resist, giue fortitude, giue patience to endure, giue
<pb facs="tcp:176435:85"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> constancye that alwaies thine, that alwaies thine, I may perseuer sure. I may perseuer sure, {repeat} perseuer sure, I may perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer sure, {repeat} I may perseuer sure.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:86"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXIII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hyle that the Sunne with his beames hot, scorched the fruits in vale, in vale &amp; mountaine, and mountaine: Philon the sheperd late forgot, sitting besides a Christall fountaine, a Christall fountaine, sitting besides, sitting besides a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stal fountaine, in shadow of a, of a greene Oke tree, vppon his pipe this song playd he, this song playd he. Adew loue, adew loue, vntrue loue, vntrue loue, vntrue loue, adew loue, adew loue, your minde is light, is light, soone
<pb facs="tcp:176435:86"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> lost, soone lost for new loue, soone lost for new loue, for new loue, soone lost for new loue.</p>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <head>2</head>
                        <l>So long as I was in your sight,</l>
                        <l>I was as your hart, your soule, your treasure,</l>
                        <l>And euermore you sob'd, you sigh'd,</l>
                        <l>Burning in flames beyond all measure,</l>
                        <l>Three dayes endur'd your Loue to me,</l>
                        <l>And it was lost in other three.</l>
                        <l>Adew Loue adew loue vntrue loue,</l>
                        <l>Vntrue loue vntrue loue adew loue,</l>
                        <l>Your mynd is light, soone lost for new loue</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <head>3</head>
                        <l>Another shepherd you dyd see,</l>
                        <l>To whome your hart was soone enchayned,</l>
                        <l>Full soone your loue was leapt from me,</l>
                        <l>Full soone my place he had obtayned,</l>
                        <l>Soone came a third your loue to winne,</l>
                        <l>And we were out and he was in.</l>
                        <l>Adew loue, &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="4">
                        <head>4</head>
                        <l>Sure you haue made me passing glad,</l>
                        <l>That you your mynd so soone remoued,</l>
                        <l>Before that I the leysure had,</l>
                        <l>To chuse you for my best beloued.</l>
                        <l>For all my loue was past and dooune,</l>
                        <l>Two dayes before it was begoonne.</l>
                        <l>Adew Loue &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:87"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXIIII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eioyce, re╌ioyce, with hart and voyce, and voyce, in Christ his byrth this day, re╌ioyce, re╌ioyce, in Christ his birth this day, this day reioyce, re╌ioyce, reioyce, re╌ioyce, reioyce, re╌ioyce, reioyce, re╌ioyce, re╌ioyce, re╌ioyce, re╌ioyce. </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:87"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXV. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ast of all doubtfull, doubtfull care, exile and banish teares, to ioyfull newes de╌uine, de╌uine, to ioyfull newes de╌uine, to ioyfull newes de╌uine, lend vs your listning eares. lend vs your listning eares, lend vs your listning eares, your listning eares, listning eares, your listning eares, listning eares, lend vs your listning eares.</p>
                     <trailer>¶ <hi>Heere endeth the songs of foure parts.</hi>
                     </trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="song">
                     <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:88"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Enelope that longed for the sight, for the sight, Pe╌nelope that longed for the sight of her Vlisses, wandring all to long, felt neuer ioy wherein she tooke delyght, wherin she tooke de╌light, {repeat} although she liu'd in greatest ioyes a╌mong, so I, so I poore wretch, possessing that I craue, I craue, that I craue, both liue and lacke, and lacke, both liue and lacke, by wrong of that I haue, I haue: Then blame me not, {repeat} blame me not although to heauens I crye, I crye, and pray the gods, {repeat} that shortly I might dye. that shortly I might dye, that I myght dye: Then blame me not, then
<pb facs="tcp:176435:88"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> blame me not, blame me not, although to heauens I crye, I cry, and pray the gods, {repeat} that shortly I might dye, that shortly I might dye, that I might dye, that I might dye, myght dye, {repeat} that I myght dye, {repeat} that I myght dye, that I myght dye.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:89"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVIII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ompell the Hauke to sit that is vnmand, that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand compell the Hawke to sit, to fit, that is vnmand, vnmand, or make the Hound vntaught, to draw the Deere, {repeat} or bring the free against his will in band, against his will in band, against his will in band, in band, or moue the sad a plea╌sant tale to heae, a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant tale to heare, to heare, your tyme is lost, and you are neare the neere, neare the neere, &amp; you are neare the neere, are neare the neere, So Loue, ne learnes by force the knot to knit, ne learnes by force the knot to knit, he serues
<pb facs="tcp:176435:89"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> but those that feele sweete fancies fitt, that feele sweet fancyes fitt, he serues but those that feele sweet fancies fitt. So loue ne &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:90"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXIX. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ee those sweet eyes, those sweete eyes, see, see those sweet eyes, those more then sweetest eyes, then sweetest eyes, eyes whom the starres exceede not in their grace, in their grace. See Loue at gaze, at gaze. See Loue at gaze, {repeat} Loue that would faine de╌uise, but cannot speake, to plead, to plead, his wondrous case.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:90"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXX. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I was otherwise then now I am, then now I am, I loued more but skilled not so much, fayre wordes and smyles, could haue contented than, contented than, my simple age &amp; ignorance, my simple age and ingnorance was such, was such: But at the length, the length, but at the length, {repeat} experience, experience made me wonder, that harts and tongues did lodge so farre, so farre as╌sunder, but at the length, {repeat} experience made me wonder, ex╌perience made me wonder, that harts and tongues, {repeat} did lodge so farre assunder, that harts and tongues, {repeat} did lodge so farre, so farre assunder▪</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:91"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXI. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VHen first by force of fatall desteny, from Carthage towne the Troyan knyght, the Troyan knight did sayle, Queene Dido fayre, with wofull wepyng eye, {repeat} his strange depart, did greauously bewayle, bewaile, did greauosly bewaile: And when no sighes nor teares, could ease her smart, her smart, with sword full sharpe, full sharpe, with sword full sharpe, she pearst her tender hart, she pearst her tender hart, her tender hart. And when no &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:91"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thought that loue had beene a boy, {repeat} with blynded eyes, blynded eyes, or else some other, some other wanton toy that men deuise, deuise, like tales of fayryes of fayryes often told, by doting age that dyes for cold, for cold, lyke tales of fayryes, of fayryes often told, by doting age that dyes for cold, that dyes for cold, by doting age that dyes for cold, for cold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:92"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXIII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Deere life when may it be, {repeat} that mine eyes, that mine eyes thine eyes may see, thine eyes may see, and in them my minde discouer, whether absence hath had force, hath had force, thy remembrance to deforce, to deforce, from the Image of thy louer, {repeat} of thy louer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:92"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXIIII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oue would discharge, dis╌charge, loue would dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, the dewty of his hart, of his hart, in beauties praise, whose greatnes doth de╌nye, whose greatnes doth de╌nye, wordes to his thougths, to his thoughts, words to his thoughts, {repeat} &amp; houghts to her de╌sart, desart, which high conceyts since nothing can supply, nothing can supply, Loue heere constraynd, through conquest to confesse, through conquest to confesse, confesse, byds si╌lence sighe, sighe, that tongue cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse. Loue heere &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:93"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXV. TENOR. A Carowle for Christmas day, the quire whereof (Reioyce) being of 4 parts, is the XXIIII. song.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> FRom Virgins wombe, &amp;c. </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>FRom Virgins wombe this day did spring,</l>
                        <l>The precious seed that saued man,</l>
                        <l>This day let man reioyce and sweetly sing</l>
                        <l>Since on this day saluacion first began,</l>
                        <l>This day dyd Christ mans soule from death remoue</l>
                        <l>With glorious Saints to dwell in heauen aboue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>This day to man came pledge of perfect peace,</l>
                        <l>This day to man came loue and vnitie,</l>
                        <l>This day mans griefe began for to surcease,</l>
                        <l>This day dyd man receiue a remedie,</l>
                        <l>For each offence and euery deadly sinne,</l>
                        <l>With guiltie hart that earst he wandred in.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>In Christ his flock let loue be surely plast,</l>
                        <l>From Christ his flock let concord hate expell,</l>
                        <l>Of Christ his flock let loue be so embrast,</l>
                        <l>As we in Christ, and Christ in vs may dwell,</l>
                        <l>Christ is the Author of sweet vnitie,</l>
                        <l>From whence procedeth all felicitie.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O sing vnto this glittering glorious king,</l>
                        <l>O praise his name let euery liuing thing,</l>
                        <l>Let hart and voyce like bells of siluer ring,</l>
                        <l>The comfort that this day to man doth bring,</l>
                        <l>Let Lute, let Shalme, with sound of sweet delight,</l>
                        <l>These ioyes of Christ his birth this day resight.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:93"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. The first part. XXXVI. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F gold all burnisht, and brighter then sunne beames, were those curled lockes vppon her noble head, from whose deepe conceits, my true deseruings flead, deseruinges flead, wherfore these mine eyes, {repeat} such store of teares out streames, such store of teares, of teares out streames. Her eyes are faire starrs, her red like damaske rose, her white siluer shyne of Moone, on Christall streame, her beauty perfect, wheron my fancies dreame, my fancies dreame, her lippes are rubies, her teeth of pearle two rowes, two rowes, her teeth of pearle two rowes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="37" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:94"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. The second part. XXXVII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> HEr breath is more sweet, is more sweet, then perfect, then perfect Amber is, her yeeres are in prime, and nothing doth she want, {repeat} doth she want, that might draw Angells from Heauen to further blisse, that might draw Angells from Heauen to further blisse, {repeat} to further blisse, of all things perfect, perfect, this do I most complaine, complaine, her hart is a rock made all of Adamant, made all of Adamant, of Adamant, which guifts all delight, all delight {repeat} delight, this last doth onely paine, this last doth onely paine, {repeat} this last doth onely paine, this last doth onely paine, {repeat} doth one╌ly paine.</p>
                     <trailer>¶ Heere endeth the songs of 5. parts.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="38" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:94"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XXXVIII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold how good a thing it is, how good a thing it is, it is, for bretheren to agree, when men amongst them do no stryfe, but peace and concord see, {repeat} full lyke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pretious balme, the pretious balme, full like vnto the pretious balme, from Arons heed that fell, from Arons hed that fell, {repeat} and did descend, vp╌pon his beard, his garment skirts vntyll, vn╌tyll, his garment skyrts vn╌tyll, his garment skyrts vn╌tyll, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll, his garment skyrts vntyll.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="39" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:95"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XXXIX. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND as the pleasant morning dew, morning dew, the Mountaynes doth releeue, the Mountaines doth releeue, {repeat} {repeat} so God wil blesse wher concord is, {repeat} {repeat} where concord is, and lyfe, and lyfe eter╌nall giue, and lyfe eternall giue, eternall giue, and lyfe eternall giue, giue, and life eter╌nall giue, {repeat} {repeat}</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="40" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:95"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. XL. TENOR. A Carowle for Christmas day, the quire whereof (Cast of all doubtfull care) being of 4. parts, is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> XXV. song.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> An earthly tree. </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>AN earthly tree a heauenly fruit it bare,</l>
                        <l>A case of clay containd a crowne immortall,</l>
                        <l>A crowne of crownes, a king whose cost &amp; care</l>
                        <l>Redeemd poore man, whose race before was thrall</l>
                        <l>To death, to dome, to paines of euerlasting,</l>
                        <l>By his sweet death, skornes, strypes, &amp; often fasting.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Starre aboue the Starres, a Sonne of light,</l>
                        <l>Whose blessed beames this wretched earth bespred</l>
                        <l>With hope of Heauen and of Gods sonne the sight</l>
                        <l>Which in our flesh and sinfull soule lay dead,</l>
                        <l>O fayth, O hope, O ioyes renownd for euer,</l>
                        <l>O liuely lyfe that deathlesse shall perseuer.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then let vs sing the Iullabyes of sleepe,</l>
                        <l>To this sweet babe, borne to awake vs all,</l>
                        <l>From drowsie sinne that made old Adam weepe,</l>
                        <l>And by his fault gauē to mankinde the fall,</l>
                        <l>For loe this day, the byrth day, day of dayes,</l>
                        <l>Somons our songs to giue him laud &amp; praise.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="41" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:96"/>
                     <head>Of 6. A Dialogue betwen two Sheperds. XLI. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> WHo made thee Hob, &amp;c. </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="42" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:96"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XLII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND think ye Nimphes to scorne at loue, to scorne at loue, {repeat} as if his fire were but of strawes, {repeat} he made y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> myghtye godds aboue, to stoope &amp; bowe vnto his lawes, his lawes, &amp; with his shaft of beauty bright, {repeat} he slayes the harts that scorne his might, that scorne his myght. And with his shaft of beauty bryght, {repeat} he slayes the harts that scorne his might, that scorne his might.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:97"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XLIII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oue is a fit of pleasure, of pleasure, loue is a fitt of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, bred out of Idle braynes, {repeat} his fancies haue no measure, no more then haue his pains: his vayne affections lyke the wether, lyke the wether, {repeat} the wether, precise or fond, we wot not whether, we wot not whe╌ther, we wot not whether.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="44" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:97"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. XLIIII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> IF in thine hart thou nourish will and giue all to thy lust, then sorowes sharpe &amp; griefes at length, {repeat} endure of force thou must, {repeat} endure of force thou must, of force thou must, but if that reason rule thy will &amp; gouerne al thy minde, thy mynde, a blessed life then shalt thou leade, then shalt thou lead, a blessed life then shalt thou lead, and fewest daungers finde, daungers finde, {repeat} and fewest daungers finde, daungers finde, and fewest daungers finde, {repeat} and fewest daungers finde, and few╌est daungers finde.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="45" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:98"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. XLV. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto the hills myne eyes I lyft, myne eyes I lyft, vnto the hills, the hills, my hope shall neuer fade, but from the Lord I looke for helpe, {repeat} that Heauen and earth hath made, {repeat} hath made. Thy foote he will from slipping saue, he will from slypping saue, and he that doth thee keepe, with watchfull eye will thee preserue, {repeat} without slomber or sleepe. {repeat} or sleepe. The Lord thy keeper and shade is, and stands at thy right arme, the Sunne by day shall not thee burne, nor Moone by nyght thee harme, the Sunne by day shall not thee burne, nor Moone by night
<pb facs="tcp:176435:98"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> thee harme, The Lord shall keepe thee from all yll, thy soule he shall preserue, he shall preserue, thy soule he shall pre╌serue, and all thy waies both in and out, {repeat} both in and out, for euer shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue. for euer shall conserue, {repeat} shall conserue, for euer shall con╌serue, {repeat} shall conserue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="46" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:99"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XLVI. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> CHrist rising againe. Death from henceforth, {repeat} hath no power vppon him, to put away sinne, {repeat} And so likewise count your selues, count your selues dead vnto sinne, but lyuing, but lyuing vnto God, In Christ Iesus our Lord, {repeat} Iesus our Lord. </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="47" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:99"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XLVII. TENOR.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> CHrist is risen againe, &amp;c. Christ is risen againe, againe, the first fruits of them that sleepe, of them that sleepe, the first fruits of thē that sleep, foreseeing, that by man came death. for as by Adam, all men do dye, all men do dye, do dye. So by Christ, so by Christ, by Christ, all men shalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored to lyfe, all men shalbe restored to life, restored to life, all men {repeat} shalbe restored to lyfe, to lyfe, shalbe restored to life, restored to lyfe,
<pb facs="tcp:176435:99"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> to lyfe. Amen. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:100"/>
                  <head>¶ <hi>A Table of all the songs contained in these Bookes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 3. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>LOrd in thy rage. I</item>
                        <item>Right blest are they. II</item>
                        <item>Lord in thy wrath. III</item>
                        <item>O God which art most mercifull. IIII</item>
                        <item>Lord heare my prayer instantly. V</item>
                        <item>From depth of sinne O Lord. VI</item>
                        <item>Attend myne humble prayer Lord. VII</item>
                        <item>Susanna fayre. VIII</item>
                        <item>The Nightingale. IX</item>
                        <item>When yonglings first. 1 part. X</item>
                        <item>But when by poofe. 2 part. XI</item>
                        <item>Vppon a sommers day. 1 part. XII</item>
                        <item>Then for a bote. 2 part. XIII</item>
                        <item>The greedy Hauke. XIIII</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 4. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>IS Loue a boy. 1 part. XV</item>
                        <item>Boy pittie mee. 2 part. XVI</item>
                        <item>Wounded I am. 1 part. XVII</item>
                        <item>Yet of vs twaine. 2 part. XVIII</item>
                        <item>From Citheron. 1 part. XIX</item>
                        <item>There carelesse thoughts 2 part. XX</item>
                        <item>If Loue be iust. 3 part. XXI</item>
                        <item>O Lord my God. XXII</item>
                        <item>While that the Sunne. XXIII</item>
                        <item>Reioyce, reioyce. XXIIII</item>
                        <item>Cast of all doubtfull care▪ XXV</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 5. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>WEeping full sore. XXVI</item>
                        <item>Penelope. XXVII</item>
                        <item>Compell y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Hauke to sit. XXVIII</item>
                        <item>See, see those sweet eyes. XXIX</item>
                        <item>When I was otherwise then now I am. XXX</item>
                        <item>When first by force. XXXI</item>
                        <item>I thought that loue had bene a boy. XXXII</item>
                        <item>O deere lyfe when may it be. XXXIII</item>
                        <item>Loue would discharge. XXXIIII</item>
                        <item>From Virgins wombe. XXXV</item>
                        <item>Of gold all burnisht. 1. part. XXXVI</item>
                        <item>Her breath is more sweet. 2. part. XXXVII</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 6. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>BEhold how good a thing it is. 1 part. XXXVIII</item>
                        <item>And as the pleasant mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dew. 2 part. XXXIX</item>
                        <item>An earthly tree. XL</item>
                        <item>Who made thee Hob. XLI</item>
                        <item>And think ye Nymphes. 1. part. XLII</item>
                        <item>Loue is a fit of pleasure. 2. part. XLIII</item>
                        <item>If in thine hart. XLIIII</item>
                        <item>Vnto the hills. XLV</item>
                        <item>Christ rising againe. 1 part. XLVI</item>
                        <item>Christ is risen againe. 2. part. XLVII</item>
                     </list>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London by Thomas East, dwelling in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dersgate streete, at the signe of the blacke Horse.</hi> 1589.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:100"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:101"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:101"/>
                  <head>SEXTVS.</head>
                  <p>¶ Songs of sundrie natures, some of grauitie, and others of myrth, fit for all compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and voyces. Lately made and composed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Musicke of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts: and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished for the delight of all such as take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in the exercise of that Art.</p>
                  <p>By VVilliam Byrd, one of the Gentlemen of the Queenes Maiesties honorable Chappell.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device (?) not found in McKerrow</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Thomas East, the assigne of William Byrd, and are to be sold at the house of the sayd T. East, being in Aldersgate streete, at the signe of the blacke Horse. 1589.</p>
                  <p>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:102"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:102"/>
                  <head>To the right honorable my very good Lord, Sir Henry Carye, Baron of Hunsdon, knight of the most noble order of the Garter, Lord Chamberlen to the Queenes most excelent Maiestie, Lord Warden of the East Marches towards Scotland, gouernor of Barwycke and the Castle of Norham, Captaine of the Gentlemen Pencioners, Iustice in Oyer, ouer all her Maiesties Forrests and Chases, on this side the Riuer of Trent, &amp; one of her Maiesties most honorable priuie councell. William Byrd wisheth increase of honor, with all true felicitie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing obserued (Right Honorable) that since the publishing in print, of my last labors in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, diuers persons of great honor and worship, haue more esteemed &amp; delighted in the exercise of that Art, then before. And being perswaded, that the same hath the rather encreased, through their good acceptation of my former endeuors: it hath especially moued and encouraged me to take further paines to gratifie theyr curteous dispositions therevnto, knowing that the varietie and choyse of songs, is both a prayse of the Art, and a pleasure to the delighted therein. And finding no person to whome the dedication thereof so fitly and properly belonged, as vnto your Lordship, by whome (through the honorable office which you exercise about her Maiesties person) both my selfe (for my place of seruice,) &amp; all other her highnesse Musitions are to be commanded, and vnder your high aucthoritie to be protected. And for many fauors to me shewed, being most deepely bound vnto your Honor, hauing not in me any other powre of seruiseable thanckfulnesse then in notes &amp; tunes of Musicke. I most humbly beseech your Lordship to take into your Honorable protection, these my poore trauells in that Art, accepting them as seruants redy to giue your L. delight, after you haue bene forewearied in affayres of great importance. Besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching almightie God to giue you a long, healthie, and happie lyfe, with a blessed end. I humbly take my leaue.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Lordships most bounden, William Byrd.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_courteous_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:103"/>
                  <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Inding that my last Impression of Musicke (most gentle Reader) through thy curtesie and fauor, hath had good passage and vtterance: and that since the publishing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the exercise and loue of that Art to haue exceedingly encreased. I haue bene encouraged thereby, to take fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paines therein, and to make thee pertaker thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I would shew my selfe gratefull to thee for thy loue, and desirous to delight thee with varietie, whereof (in my opinion) no Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is more plentifully adorned then Musicke. For which purpose I do now publish for thee, songs of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts, to serue for all companies and voyces: whereof some are easie and plaine to sing, other more hard and difi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, but all, such as any yong practicioner in singing, with a little foresight, may easely performe. If I finde thy curtesie to extend aswell to these my present trauells, as it hath done to my former endeuors, I will make my selfe endebted to thee during my lyfe, of whatsoeuer is in me, to yeeld thy delight in Musick, any satisfaction.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The most affectionate freend to all that loue or learne Musick William Byrd.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="sextus" type="partbook">
                  <div n="38" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:103"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XXXVIII. SEXTVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold how good a thing it is, for brethren to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, when men amongst them do no strife, but peace and concord see, full lyke vnto the pretious balme, full like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pretious balme, the preti╌ous balme, from Arons head that fell, that fell, from Arons head that fell, that fell, from Arons head that fell, and did descend vppon his beard, his garment skyrts vn╌tyll. and did descend vppon his beard, and did descend vpon his beard, his garment skyrts vntyll, vn╌tyl, his garment skyrts vn╌tyll.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="39" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:104"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XXXIX. SEXTVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND as the pleasant morning dew, the pleasant morning dew, morning dew, the pleasant mor╌ning dew, the Mountaynes doth re╌leeue, {repeat} so God will blesse wher con╌cord is, {repeat} so God will blesse where con╌cord is, will blesse wher concord is, and lyfe eternall giue, {repeat} {repeat} and lyfe eternall giue, {repeat} eternall giue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="40" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:104"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. XL. SEXTVS. A Carowle for Christmas day, the quire whereof (Cast of all doubtfull care) being of 4. parts, is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> XXV. song.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N earthly tree a heauenly fruit it bare a crowne of crownes a king whose cost and care to death, to doome, to paines of euer╌lasting, by his sweete death, {repeat} skornes, stripes, and of╌ten fasting, skornes, stripes and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten fasting.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>AN earthly tree a heauenly fruit it bare,</l>
                        <l>A case of clay containd a crowne immortall,</l>
                        <l>A crowne of crownes, a king whose cost &amp; care</l>
                        <l>Redeemd poore man, whose race before was thrall</l>
                        <l>To death, to dome, to paines of euerlasting,</l>
                        <l>By his sweet death, skornes, strypes, &amp; often fasting.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Starre aboue the Starres, a Sonne of light,</l>
                        <l>Whose blessed beames this wretched earth bespred</l>
                        <l>With hope of Heauen and of Gods sonne the sight</l>
                        <l>Which in our flesh and sinfull soule lay dead,</l>
                        <l>O fayth, O hope, O ioyes renownd for euer,</l>
                        <l>O liuely lyfe that deathlesse shall perseuer.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then let vs sing the Iullabyes of sleepe,</l>
                        <l>To this sweet babe, borne to awake vs all,</l>
                        <l>From drowsie sinne that made old Adam weepe,</l>
                        <l>And by his fault gaue to mankinde the fall,</l>
                        <l>For loe this day, the byrth day, day of dayes,</l>
                        <l>Somons our songs to giue him laud &amp; praise.</l>
                        <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="41" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:105"/>
                     <head>Of 6. A Dialogue betwen two Sheperds. XLI. SEXTVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho made the hob, forsake the Plowe, and fall in loue, what dost thou serue a shepperdesse▪ what is her name, who beares thy hart within her brest, Oh Hob, I feare she looks to hye, oh Hob, I feare she lookes to hye, oh Hob, I feare she lookes to hye, yet loue I must or else I dye, I dye, or else I dye, I dye.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="42" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:105"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XLII. SEXTVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND thinke ye Nymphes to scorne at loue, as if his fire were but of strawes, he made the myghtye godds aboue, to stoope &amp; bowe vnto his lawes, and with his shafts of bewty bright, he slayes the harts that scorne his might. And with his shafts of beauty bryght, he slayes the harts that scorne his myght.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:106"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XLIII. SEXTVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oue is a fitt of pleasure, bred out of Idle brains, his fancies haue no measure, no more then haue his pains. his vaine affections lyke the wether, precise or fond, {repeat} we wot not whether, we wot not whether.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="44" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:106"/>
                     <head>Of 6. XLIIII. SEXTVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> IF in thine hart thou nourish will &amp; giue all to thy lust, and giue all to thy lust, to thy lust, then sorowes sharpe and griefes at length, at length, endure of force thou must, {repeat} endure of force thou must. But if that reason rule thy will and gouerne all thy minde, {repeat} a blessed lyfe then shalt thou leade, shalt thou leade, a blessed lyfe then shalt thou lead, {repeat} and fewest daungers find, daun╌gers finde, and sewest dangers find, {repeat} and sewest daun╌gers find, and fewest daungers finde, and fewest daungers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="45" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:107"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. Psal. 121. XLV. SEXTVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto the hills myne eyes I lyft, myne eyes I lyft, my hope shall neuer fade, shall neuer fade, but from the Lord I looke for helpe, that Heauen and earth hath made. Thy foote he will from slipping saue, and he that doth thee keepe, that doth thee keepe, and he that doth thee keepe, with watchfull eye, will thee preserue, {repeat} pre╌serue, without slomber or sleepe, or sleepe. The Lord thy keeper &amp; shade is, and shade is, and stands at thy right arme. The Lord shall keepe thee from all ill, thy soule he
<pb facs="tcp:176435:107"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> shall pre╌serue, {repeat} and all thy waies both in &amp; out, for euer shall conserue, con╌serue, for euer shall conserue, {repeat} {repeat} for euer shall conserue, {repeat} for euer shall conserue, shall conserue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="46" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:108"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XLVI. SEXTVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> CHrist rising, Christ rising againe from the deade, now dyeth not, now dyeth not, now dyeth not, for in that he dy'd, he dy'd but once to put away sinne, to put away sinne, but in that he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth he lyueth vnto God, he lyueth vnto God, he lyueth vnto God, And so likewise count your selues, count your selues dead vnto sinne, but liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but liuing vnto God, In Christ Iesus our Lord, In Christ Iesus our Lord, In Christ Iesus our Lord. </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="47" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:108"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XLVII. SEXTVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> CHrist is risen agayne, the first fruits of them that sleepe, of them that sleepe, Christ is risen againe, a╌gaine Christ is risen againe, the first fruits of them that sleepe, of them that sleepe, foreseing that by man came death, by man also, by man also, commeth the resurrexcion of the dead, of the dead, of the dead, so by Christ, so by Christ, all men shalbe restored, {repeat} shalbe restored to lyfe, {repeat} restored to life, to life, to life, to life, to life, so by Christ, so by Christ, by Christ, all mē shalbe restored to life, all men shalbe restred to lyfe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored to life, all men shall be restored to lyfe, restored to lyfe, resto╌red
<pb facs="tcp:176435:108"/> to lyfe, {repeat} restored to lyfe. A men.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:109"/>
                  <head>¶ <hi>A Table of all the songs contained in these Bookes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head>Of 3. parts.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>LOrd in thy rage. I</item>
                     <item>Right blest are they. II</item>
                     <item>Lord in thy wrath. III</item>
                     <item>O God which art most mercifull. IIII</item>
                     <item>Lord heare my prayer instantly. V</item>
                     <item>From depth of sinne O Lord. VI</item>
                     <item>Attend myne humble prayer Lord. VII</item>
                     <item>Susanna fayre. VIII</item>
                     <item>The Nightingale. IX</item>
                     <item>When yonglings first, 1 part. X</item>
                     <item>But when by proofe. 2 part. XI</item>
                     <item>Vppon a sommers day. 1 part. XII</item>
                     <item>Then for a bote. 2 part. XIII</item>
                     <item>The greedy Hauke. XIIII</item>
                  </list>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 4. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>IS Loue a boy. 1 part. XV</item>
                        <item>Boy pittie mee. 2 part. XVI</item>
                        <item>Wounded I am. 1 part. XVII</item>
                        <item>Yet of vs twaine. 2 part. XVIII</item>
                        <item>From Citheron. 1 part. XIX</item>
                        <item>There carelesse thoughts 2 part. XX</item>
                        <item>If Loue be iust. 3 part. XXI</item>
                        <item>O Lord my God. XXII</item>
                        <item>While that the Sunne. XXIII</item>
                        <item>Reioyce, reioyce. XXIIII</item>
                        <item>Cast of all doubtfull care▪ XXV</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 5. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>WEeping full sore. XXVI</item>
                        <item>Penelope. XXVII</item>
                        <item>Compell y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Hauke to sit. XXVIII</item>
                        <item>See, see those sweet eyes. XXIX</item>
                        <item>When I was otherwise then now I am. XXX</item>
                        <item>When first by force. XXXI</item>
                        <item>I thought that loue had bene a boy. XXXII</item>
                        <item>O deere lyfe when may it be. XXXIII</item>
                        <item>Loue would discharge. XXXIIII</item>
                        <item>From Virgins wombe. XXXV</item>
                        <item>Of gold all burnisht. 1. part. XXXVI</item>
                        <item>Her breath is more sweet. 2. part. XXXVII</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 6. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>BEhold how good a thing it is, 1 part. XXXVIII</item>
                        <item>And as the pleasant morning dew. 2 part. XXXIX</item>
                        <item>An earthly tree. XL</item>
                        <item>Who made thee Hob. XLI</item>
                        <item>And think ye Nymphes. 1. part. XLII</item>
                        <item>Loue is a fit of pleasure. 2. part. XLIII</item>
                        <item>If in thine hart. XLIIII</item>
                        <item>Vnto the hills. XLV</item>
                        <item>Christ rising againe. 1 part. XLVI</item>
                        <item>Christ is risen againe. 2. part. XLVII</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London by Thomas East, dwelling in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dersgate streete, at the signe of the blacke Horse.</hi> 1589.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:109"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:110"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:110"/>
                  <p>BASSVS.</p>
                  <p>¶ Songs of sundrie natures, some of grauitie, and others of myrth, fit for all compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and voyces. Lately made and composed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Musicke of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts: and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished for the delight of all such as take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in the exercise of that Art.</p>
                  <p>By VVilliam Byrd, one of the Gentlemen of the Queenes Maiesties honorable Chappell.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device (?) not found in McKerrow</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Thomas East, the assigne of William Byrd, and are to be sold at the house of the sayd T. East, being in Aldersgate streete, at the signe of the blacke Horse. 1589.</p>
                  <p>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:111"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:111"/>
                  <head>To the right honorable my very good Lord, Sir Henry Carye, Baron of Hunsdon, knight of the most noble order of the Garter, Lord Chamberlen to the Queenes most excelent Maiestie, Lord Warden of the East Marches towards Scotland, gouernor of Barwycke and the Castle of Norham, Captaine of the Gentlemen Pencioners, Iustice in Oyer, ouer all her Maiesties Forrests and Chases, on this side the Riuer of Trent, &amp; one of her Maiesties most honorable priuie councell. William Byrd wisheth increase of honor, with all true felicitie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing obserued (Right Honorable) that since the publishing in print, of my last labors in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, diuers persons of great honor and worship, haue more esteemed &amp; delighted in the exercise of that Art, then before. And being perswaded, that the same hath the rather encreased, through their good acceptation of my former endeuors: it hath especially moued and encouraged me to take further paines to gratifie theyr curteous dispositions therevnto, knowing that the varietie and choyse of songs, is both a prayse of the Art, and a pleasure to the delighted therein. And finding no person to whome the dedication thereof so fitly and properly belonged, as vnto your Lordship, by whome (through the honorable office which you exercise about her Maiesties person) both my selfe (for my place of seruice,) &amp; all other her highnesse Musitions are to be commanded, and vnder your high aucthoritie to be protected. And for many fauors to me shewed, being most deepely bound vnto your Honor, hauing not in me any other powre of seruiseable thanckfulnesse then in notes &amp; tunes of Musicke. I most humbly beseech your Lordship to take into your Honorable protection, these my poore trauells in that Art, accepting them as seruants redy to giue your L. delight, after you haue bene forewearied in affayres of great importance. Besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching almightie God to giue you a long, healthie, and happie lyfe, with a blessed end. I humbly take my leaue.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Lordships most bounden, William Byrd.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_courteous_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:112"/>
                  <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Inding that my last Impression of Musicke (most gentle Reader) through thy curtesie and fauor, hath had good passage and vtterance: and that since the publishing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the exercise and loue of that Art to haue exceedingly encreased. I haue bene encouraged thereby, to take fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paines therein, and to make thee pertaker thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I would shew my selfe gratefull to thee for thy loue, and desirous to delight thee with varietie, whereof (in my opinion) no Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is more plentifully adorned then Musicke. For which purpose I do now publish for thee, songs of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts, to serue for all companies and voyces: whereof some are easie and plaine to sing, other more hard and difi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, but all, such as any yong practicioner in singing, with a little foresight, may easely performe. If I finde thy curtesie to extend aswell to these my present trauells, as it hath done to my former endeuors, I will make my felfe endebted to thee during my lyfe, of whatsoeuer is in me, to yeeld thy delight in Musick, any satisfaction.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The most affectionate freend to all that loue or learne Musick William Byrd.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="bass" type="partbook">
                  <div n="1" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:112"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Domine ne in furore.</hi> Psal. 6. 1. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord in thy rage rebuke me not, rebuke me not, for my most greauous sinne, nor in thine anger chasten me, but let me fauour winne, {repeat} fauour winne, haue mercy Lord on me, {repeat} on me, because my state is weake to see, {repeat} heale me, O Lord, heale me, O Lord, O Lord, O Lord, for that my bones, {repeat} are troubled sore in me, are troubled sore, are troubled sore in me, are troubled sore in me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:113"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Beati quorum.</hi> Psal. 32. II. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight blest are they whose wicked sinnes, by God remit╌ted be, remitted be, and whose defaults are couered, through his great clemencye. The man is blest, {repeat} is blest, is blest, the man is blest, to whom our Lord, our Lord, {repeat} hath not imputed sinne, impu╌ted, sinne, hath not impu╌ted sinne, nor in his spyrit, deceyt is found, {repeat} deceyt is found, nor takes delyght there in. {repeat} nor takes delyght therin, {repeat} delight therein, therein, nor takes delight therein.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:113"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Domine ne.</hi> Psal. 38. III. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord in thy wrath, correct me not, nor in thy fury vexe, nor in, nor in thy fu╌rie vexe, giue teares, giue teares, giue grace, giue penitence, vnto my sinnefull sexe, my sinfull sexe, for that the arrowes of thy wrath, thy wrath, are fixed in my hart, in my hart, and thou hast layd thine hand one me, {repeat} on me, for my most iust de╌sert, for my most iust de╌sert, for my most iust de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert, most iust desert.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:114"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Miserere mei Deus.</hi> Psal. 51. IIII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God which art most mercyfull, {repeat} haue mer╌cy Lord on me, on me, haue mer╌cy Lord on me, on me, according to thy mercy great, let me releaued be, releaued be, let me releaued be, releaued be. And put away my wickednes, my wickednes, {repeat} {repeat} And put away my wickednesse, which sundry wayes hath beene, {repeat} according to the multitude, to the multitude, according to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, to the multitude of thy compassions seene, according to the mul╌ti╌tude, to the multitude, of thy compassions seene, of thy compassions seene.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:114"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Domine exaudi.</hi> Psal. 102. V. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord heare my prayer instantlye, which I before thee make, and let my crye come vnto thee, do not the same forsake, forsake, {repeat} Turne not away thy face from me, {repeat} when troubles me oppresse, each day inclyne thyne eare to me, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyne thine eare to me, and succour my distresse, and suc╌cour my distresse, and succour my distresse.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:115"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>De profundis</hi> Psal. 130. VI. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom depth of sinne, {repeat} O Lord to thee, to thee, I haue made hum╌ble crye, Lord heare my voice, make it assend vnto thy throne so hye, vnto the voyce of my request, pour'd out before thy sight, before thy sight, before thy sight, Lord let thine eares attentiue be, attentiue be, to heare me day and night. {repeat} day and night, to heare me day and night, to heare me day and night.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:115"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. <hi>Domine exaudi.</hi> Psal. 143. VII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ttend mine humble prayer Lord, {repeat} with thine attentiue eare, attentiue eare, euen in thy truth, {repeat} and Iustyce Lord, vouchsafe my sute to heare, {repeat} vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe my sute to heare. And into Iudgemēt en╌ter not, {repeat} with thy▪ poore seruant heere, poore seruant heere, with thy poore seruant heere, because none shalbe Iusti╌fy'd, &amp; stand before thee cleere. {repeat} before thee cleere, &amp; stand before thee cleere, before thee cleere, and stand before thee cleere, {repeat} because none shalbe Iusti╌fi'd, &amp; stād be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore▪ thee cleere, and stand before thee cleere. {repeat}</p>
                     <trailer>Heere endeth the Psalmes.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:116"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. VIII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vsanna fayre sometime, sometime assaulted was by two old men desiring their delight, which leude intent they thought to bring to passe, to bring to passe, if not by tender loue, by force &amp; myght, {repeat} by force and might, to whom she sayd, {repeat} if I your sute denye, deny, you will me falsely accuse, and make me dye, and make me dye. And if I graunt, to that which you request, my chasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye shall then defloured be, {repeat} which is so deere to me, to me, that I detest my lyfe, my life, if it berefted be from mee, and rather would I dye of
<pb facs="tcp:176435:116"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> mine accord, of mine accord, {repeat} ten thousand times, {repeat} ten thousand times, then once, then once offend our Lord, offend our Lord.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:117"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. IX. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Nightingale so pea╌sant and so gay, in greene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood groues, delights to make his dwelling▪ in fields to flye, to flye, chanting his roundelaye, chanting his roun╌de╌laye, his roundelay, at lybertye against the Cage rebelling▪ against the Cage rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, rebell╌ing. But my poore hart, my poore hart, but my poore hart with sorowes ouerswelling, {repeat} through bondage vyle, bynding my freedome short, my freedome short, my freedome short, my freedome short, no plea╌sure takes, no pleasure takes, in
<pb facs="tcp:176435:117"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> these his sports excelling, in these his sports excelling, nor in his song receyueth no comfort, nor in his song receiueth no comfort, nor in his song receiueth no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, nor in his song receiueth no comfort.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:118"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. The first part. X. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen younglyngs first on Cupide fyxe their sight, and see him naked, blyndfold &amp; a boy, though bow &amp; shafts and fier╌brand be his might, yet weene they he can worke them none anoy, {repeat} anoy. yet weene they he can worke them none a╌noy. And therefore with his purpill wings they play, for glorious semeth loue though lyght as fether, and when they haue done, they weene to skape a way, for blynd men say they {repeat} shoote they know not whether. {repeat} shoote they know not whether {repeat} {repeat} not whether.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:118"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. The second part. XI. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt when by proofe they finde that he did see, did see, &amp; that his wound did rather dym their sight, they wonder more how such a lad as he, {repeat} should be of such surpassing powre &amp; myght: should be of such, surpassing powre and might, {repeat} surpassing powre and might: but Ants haue gals, {repeat} so hath the Bee his styng, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Bee his sting, so hath the Bee his sting, then sheeld me heauens from such a sub╌tyle thing▪ then sheeld me heauens from such a subtyle thing, then {repeat} from such a subtyle thing, {repeat} from such a subtyle thing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:119"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. The first part. XII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ppon a Somers day, loue went to swym, {repeat} &amp; cast himselfe into a Sea of teares, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> clouds cald in their light, &amp; heauē waxt dyme, &amp; sighes did raise a tempest causing feares {repeat} The naked boy, {repeat} could not so wyld his armes, but that the waues were maisters of his might, of his might, and threatned him to worke farre greater harmes, farre greater harmes, and threatned him to worke farre greater harmes, if he deuysed not to skape by flyght▪ by flyght, if he deuised not to skape by flyght, to skape by flyght.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:119"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. The second part. XIII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hen for a bote his quiuer stoode in stead, his quiuer stoode in steade, his bow vnbent did serue him for a mast, whereby to sayle his cloth of vayle, whereby to sayle his cloth of vayle, his cloth of vayle he spread, and shafts for ores on either bord he cast, {repeat} and shafts for ores on either bord he cast, from shypwracke safe, this wag got thus to shore, {repeat} got thus to shore, and sware, and sware, to bath in louers teares no more, {repeat} to bath in louers teares no more, no more.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:120"/>
                     <head>Of 3. voc. XIIII. BASSVS</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He greedy Hawke, {repeat} with sooden sight of lure, doth stoope, doth stoope, in hope to haue her wished pray, her wished pray, so, many men do stoope, {repeat} to syghts vnsure, and curteous speach, {repeat} doth keepe them at the bay, the bay, let them beware least frēdly lookes be lyke, be lyke, the lure, whereat the so╌ring Hawke did stryke▪ did stryke, whereat the so╌ryng Hawk did strik, whereat the so╌ring Hawke did stryke, did stryke, the so╌ring Hawke dyd stryke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:120"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The first part. XV. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S loue a boy? {repeat} what meanes he then to strike, to strike, or is he blynde? why will he be a guide, is he a man? {repeat} why doth he hurt his like, is he a God? {repeat} why doth he men de╌ryde, deryde, why doth &amp;c. {repeat} why doth he men deryde: No one of these, {repeat} but one com╌pact of all, of all, a wilfull boy, a man still dealing blowes, of purpose blynde, {repeat} to leade men to their thrall, a God that rules, {repeat} vnruly, God he knowes, he knowes, vnruly, God he knowes, {repeat} vnruly, God he knowes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:121"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The second part. XVI. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Oy pittye me that am a child a╌gaine, that am a childe a╌gaine, blynde be no more my guide to make me stray, blynde be no more my guide, to make me stray, man vse thy might, to force away my paine, {repeat} {repeat} God do me good, {repeat} {repeat} &amp; leade me to my way, to my way, and leade me to my way, to my way: And if thou beest a powre to me vn╌knowne, to me vnknowne, powre of my life, of my life, powre of my lyfe, let heere thy grace be {repeat} showne, {repeat} let heere thy grace be showne, {repeat} And if &amp;c. </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:121"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The first part. XVII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ounded I am, and dare not seeke reliefe, and dare not seeke reliefe, for this new stroke, {repeat} vnseene but not vnfelt, vnfelt, no bloud nor bruise is witnes to my greife, {repeat} but siges, but sighes and teares wherewith I mourne and melt, {repeat} wherwith I mourne and melt, I mourne &amp; melt, if I complaine my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is suspect, {repeat} if I containe, {repeat} with cares I am vndone, vndone, sit still &amp; dye, tell truth &amp; be reiect, {repeat} O hatefull, O hatefull choyse that sorrow cannot shun, {repeat} that sorow cannot shun, that sorrow cannot shun.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:122"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The second part. XVIII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Et of vs twaine whose losse shalbe the lesse, whose losse shalbe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lesse, myne of my life, or you of your good name, good name, light is my death regarding my distresse, but your offence cryes out to your diffame, to your diffame, cryes out to your dif╌fame: A vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin fayre hath slayne for lacke of grace, of grace, the man that made an Idoll of her face, an Idoll of her face. the man that made an Idoll of her face, {repeat} of her face. A virgin▪ &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:122"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The first part. XIX. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom Citheron the warlyke boy is fled, and smilyng sits vppon a virgins lappe, thereby to trayne poore misers to the trappe, whom beauty drawes with fancye to be fedde, with fancye to be fedde, and when desire with eager lookes is ledde, and when desire with eager lookes is ledde, is ledde, then from her eyes, the arrow flyes, {repeat} fethered with flame, arm'd with a golden head, arm'd with a golden head.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:123"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The second part. XX. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here carelesse thoughts are freed of that flame, where with her thrales are scorched to the hart, are scorched to the hart, if loue would so, if loue would so, would God, would God th'enchaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng dart might once returne and burne, {repeat} from whence it came, {repeat} returne from whence it came, not to deface, {repeat} of beautyes worke the frame, but by rebownd, it might be found, {repeat} what secret smart I suffer by the same, by the same, what secret smart, I suffer by the same, {repeat} what secret smart I suffer by the same, by the same.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:123"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. The third part. XXI. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F loue be iust, loe iust is my desire, &amp; if vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iust why is he calld a God, why is he calld a God, a God, O God, O God, O iust, O iust, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue thy rod, to chasten those that from thy lawes retyre, to chasten those that from thy lawes retyre, but chuse aright, {repeat} good loue I thee require, I thee require, the golden head, not that of lead, {repeat} her hart is frost and must dissolue by fire, {repeat} {repeat} and must dissolue, and must dissolue by fire, by fire.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:124"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord my God, let flesh &amp; bloud thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uāt not subdew, subdew, O Lord my God, let flesh &amp; bloud thy seruant not subdew, nor let the world deceiue me, {repeat} with his glory most vntrue, let not O Lord, O myghty God, {repeat} let not thy mortall foe, let not the feend, {repeat} with all his craft, with all his craft, thy seruāt ouerthrow, ouerthrow: But to resist, {repeat} giue fortitude, giue fortitude, giue patience to endure, giue constancy that alwayes thine, giue constancy that alwayes thine,
<pb facs="tcp:176435:124"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> I may perseuer sure. {repeat} perseuer sure, I may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seuer sure, I may perseuer sure.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:125"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXIII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hyle that the Sunne with his beames hot, scorched the fruits in vale &amp; moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and mountaine: Philon the she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perd late forgot, sitting besides a christall fountaine, {repeat} in shadow of a greene Oke tree, Oke tree, vppon his pipe this song playd he, this song playd he. Adew loue, adew loue, vntrue loue adew loue, adew loue, your minde is light, is light, your minde is light, is light, soone lost, soone
<pb facs="tcp:176435:125"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> lost for new loue, soone lost for new loue, soone lost, soone lost for new loue.</p>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <head>2</head>
                        <l>So long as I was in your sight,</l>
                        <l>I was as your hart, your soule, your treasure,</l>
                        <l>And euermore you sob'd, you sigh'd,</l>
                        <l>Burning in flames beyond all measure,</l>
                        <l>Three dayes endur'd your Loue to me,</l>
                        <l>And it was lost in other three.</l>
                        <l>Adew Loue adew loue vntrue loue,</l>
                        <l>Vntrue loue vntrue loue adew loue,</l>
                        <l>Your mynd is light, soone lost for new loue</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <head>3</head>
                        <l>Another shepherd you dyd see,</l>
                        <l>To whome your hart was soone enchayned,</l>
                        <l>Full soone your loue was leapt from me,</l>
                        <l>Full soone my place, he had obtayned,</l>
                        <l>Soone came a third your loue to winne,</l>
                        <l>And we were out and he was in.</l>
                        <l>Adew loue, &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="4">
                        <head>4</head>
                        <l>Sure you haue made me passing glad,</l>
                        <l>That you your mynd so soone remoued,</l>
                        <l>Before that I the leysure had,</l>
                        <l>To chuse you for my best beloued.</l>
                        <l>For all my loue was past and doonne,</l>
                        <l>Two dayes before it was begoonne.</l>
                        <l>Adew Loue &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:126"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXIIII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eioyce, re╌ioyce, with hart and voyce, in Christ his byrth this day, this day re╌ioyce, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, in Christ his birth, this day reioyce, re╌ioyce, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, re╌ioyce, reioyce, re╌ioyce, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, reioyce, re╌ioyce, this day reioyce, reioyce.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:126"/>
                     <head>Of 4. voc. XXV. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ast of all doubtfull care, exile and bannish teares, to ioyfull newes de╌uine, to ioyfull newes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, {repeat} deuine, lend vs your listning eares, your listning eares, lend vs your listning eares, your listning eares, lend vs your listning eares.</p>
                     <trailer>¶ <hi>Heere endeth the songs of foure parts.</hi>
                     </trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:127"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVI. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Eping full sore, {repeat} weeping full sore, {repeat} full sore, with face as fayre as siluer, not wanting rose nor lilly white to paint it, nor lilly white to paint it, I saw a lady walke fast by a riuer, I saw a lady walke fast by a riuer, vppon whose bankes Dianaes Nimphes all dawnced, {repeat} Dianaes, Nimphes all dawnced, her beauty great {repeat} her beau╌ty great, {repeat} had diuers gods in╌chanted, a╌mong the which loue was the first transformed, loue was the first transformed, who vnto her his bow and shafts had graunted, who vnto her his bow and shafts had graunted, and by her sight, to adament was turned, {repeat} to
<pb facs="tcp:176435:127"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> adamant was turned. Alas quoth I {repeat} what meaneth this demea╌nure, so faire a dame to be so full of sorowe: No wonder quoth a Nimphe, she wanteth plea╌sure, {repeat} her teares and sighes, {repeat} ne seasse from eaue to morow, from eaue tomorow: this lady Rich is of the gifts of beauty. Rich is of the gifts of beau╌ty, but vnto her, are gifts of fortune daynty. but vnto her are gifts of fortune daynty. This lady &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:128"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Enelope that longed for the sight, for the sight, Pe╌nelope that longed for the sight, for the sight of her Vlis╌ses, wandrying all to long, felt neuer ioy wherein she tooke delyght, although she lyu'd in greatest ioyes among, so I poore wrech posess╌ing that I craue, possessing that I craue, both liue and lacke, by wrong of that I haue, of that I haue: Then blame me not, {repeat} then blame me not although to heauens, to heauens I cry, and pray the gods, {repeat} that shortly I might dye, {repeat} I myght dye: Then blame me not, {repeat} then blame me not although to heauens, to heauens I cry, and pray
<pb facs="tcp:176435:128"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> the gods, {repeat} that shortly I myght dye, that shortly I myght dye, I might dye, that I myght dye, myght dye, that I myght dye, {repeat} that I myght dye.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:129"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXVIII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ompell the Hauke to sit that is vnmand, {repeat} or make the Hound vn╌taught, to draw the Deere, to draw the Deere, or bring the free against his will in band, against his will in band, {repeat} or moue the sad a plea╌sant tale to heare, a pleasant tale to heare, to heare, your tyme is lost, and you are neare the neere, {repeat} are neare the neere. So Loue, ne learnes by force the knot to knit, the knot to knit, he serues but those that feele sweete fan╌cies fitt, he serues but those,
<pb facs="tcp:176435:129"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> but those, that feele sweet fan╌cyes fitt. So loue &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:130"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXIX. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ee, see, those sweet eyes, those sweet eyes, those more then sweetest eyes, eyes whom the starres exceede not in their grace, not in their grace. See Loue at gaze, {repeat} Loue that faine would deuise, deuise, but cannot speake to plead his wonderous case.</p>
                     <argument>
                        <p>The second part of this song, (<hi>Loue would discharge</hi>) is placed the XXXIIII. song.</p>
                     </argument>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:130"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXX. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I was otherwise then now I am, I loued more but skilled not so much, so much, fayre wordes and smyles, could haue contented than my simple age, {repeat} &amp; ignorance, was such: But at the length, {repeat} experience, {repeat} experience made me wonder, that harts and tongues did lodge so farre, so farre assunder, but at the length, {repeat} experience, {repeat} experience made me wonder, that harts and tongues did lodge so farre, so farre assunder, that harts and tongues, did lodge so farre assunder.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:131"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXI. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VHen first by force, by force of fatall desteny, from Carthage towne the Troyan knyght, the Troyan knight did sayle, Queene Dido fayre, with wofull, with wofull wepyng eye, his strange depart, {repeat} did greauously bewayle: And when no sighes nor teares, nor teares, could ease her smart, {repeat} with sword full sharpe, {repeat} full sharpe, she pearst, she pearst her tender hart, she pearst, she pearst her tender hart. And when no &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:131"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thought that loue had beene a boy, with blynded eyes, {repeat} or else some other wanton toy, some other wanton toy that men deuise, like tales of fayryes, like tales of fayryes often told, by doting age, by doting age that dyes for cold, lyke tales of fayryes, like tales of fayryes often told, by doting age that dyes for cold, {repeat} by doting age that dyes for cold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:132"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc XXXIII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Deere lyfe when may it be, when may it be, {repeat} that myne eyes thine eyes may see, thine eyes may see, {repeat} and in them my minde dis╌couer, whether absence hath had force, thy remembrance to deforce, from the Image of thy louer. from the Image of thy louer, of thy louer.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O, if I my selfe finde not,</l>
                        <l>though my parting ought forgot</l>
                        <l>Nor debard from beauties treasure</l>
                        <l>Let no tongue aspier to tell</l>
                        <l>In what hie Ioyes I shall dwell,</l>
                        <l>Onely thought aymes at the pleasure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thought therefore I will send thee</l>
                        <l>To take vp the place for me,</l>
                        <l>Long I will not after tary,</l>
                        <l>There vnseene thou maist be bold</l>
                        <l>These faire wonders to behold,</l>
                        <l>Which in them my hopes do cary.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:132"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXIIII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oue, loue would discharge, {repeat} the dewty of his hart, in beauties prayse whose greatnes, whose greatnes doth denye, wordes to his thoughts, {repeat} and thoughts, and thoughts to her desart, which hygh conceits since nothing can supply, can supply, can supply: Loue heere constraynd through conquest to confesse, byds silence sighe that tongue cannot expresse, that tongue cannot ex╌presse, expresse. Loue heere &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:133"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. XXXV. BASSVS. A Carowle for Christmas day, the quire whereof (REioyce) being of 4. parts, is the XXIIII. song.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> FRom Virgins wombe, &amp;c. </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>FRom Virgins wombe this day did spring,</l>
                        <l>The precious seed that saued man,</l>
                        <l>This day let man reioyce and sweetly sing</l>
                        <l>Since on this day saluacion first began,</l>
                        <l>This day dyd Christ mans soule from death remoue</l>
                        <l>With glorious Saints to dwell in heauen aboue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>This day to man came pledge of perfect peace,</l>
                        <l>This day to man came loue and vnitie,</l>
                        <l>This day mans griefe began for to surcease,</l>
                        <l>This day dyd man receiue a remedie,</l>
                        <l>For each offence and euery deadly sinne,</l>
                        <l>With guiltie hart that earst he wandred in.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>In Christ his flock let loue be surely plast,</l>
                        <l>From Christ his flock let concord hate expell,</l>
                        <l>Of Christ his flock let loue be so embrast,</l>
                        <l>As we in Christ, and Christ in vs may dwell,</l>
                        <l>Christ is the Author of sweet vnitie,</l>
                        <l>From whence procedeth all feliciue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O sing vnto this glittering glorious king,</l>
                        <l>O praise his name let euery liuing thing,</l>
                        <l>Let hart and voyce like bells of siluer ring,</l>
                        <l>The comfort that this day to man doth bring,</l>
                        <l>Let Lute, let Shalme, with sound of sweet delight,</l>
                        <l>These ioyes of Christ his birth this day resight.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:133"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. The first part. XXXVI. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F gold all burnisht and brighter then sunne beames, were those curled lockes vppon her noble head, from whose deepe conceits, from whose deepe conceits, my true deseruings flead, wherefore these mine eyes, such store of teares, {repeat} of teares out streames. Her eyes are faire starrs, her red like damaske rose, her white siluer shine of Moone on Christall streame, her beauty perfect, {repeat} wheron my fancies dreame, her lipps are rubies, her teeth of pearle, her teeth of pearle, of pearle two rowes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="37" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:134"/>
                     <head>Of 5. voc. The second part. XXXVII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> HEr breath is more sweet, is more sweet then perfect Amber, Amber is, her yeeres are in prime &amp; nothing doth she want, that might draw Angells frō Heauen to further blisse, to further blisse, that might draw Angells frō Heauen to further blisse, to further blisse, to further blisse: {repeat} of all things perfect, perfect this do I most complaine, complaine, her hart is a rocke made all of Adamant, which guifts all delight, {repeat} which guifts all delight, this last doth onely paine, doth onely paine, doth onely paine, this last doth onely paine, doth onely paine, this last doth one╌ly paine.</p>
                     <trailer>Heere endeth the songs of 5. parts.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="38" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:134"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XXXVIII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold how good a thing it is, it is, for brethren to agree, when men amongst them do no stryfe, but peace and concord see, and concord see, full like vnto the pretious balme, the pretious balme, from Arons head that fell, from Arons head that fell, and did descend, and did descend vppon his beard, his garment skyrts vn╌tyll. his garment skyrts vn╌tyll, and did descend vpon his beard, his garment skyrts vntyll.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="39" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:135"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XXXIX. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND as the pleasant morning dew, the pleasant morning dew, the Mountaynes doth releeue, the Mountaines doth releeue, so God will blesse wher concord is, {repeat} so God will blesse where concord is, {repeat} and lyfe eternall giue, and lyfe eter╌nall giue, {repeat} and lyfe eter╌nall giue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="40" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:135"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. XL. BASSVS. A Carowle for Christmas day, the quire whereof (Cast of all doubtfull care) being of 4. parts, is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> XXV. song.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> An earthly tree. </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>AN earthly tree a heauenly fruit it bare,</l>
                        <l>A case of clay containd a crowne immortall,</l>
                        <l>A crowne of crownes, a king whose cost &amp; care</l>
                        <l>Redeemd poore man, whose race before was thrall</l>
                        <l>To death, to dome, to paines of euerlasting,</l>
                        <l>By his sweet death, skornes, strypes, &amp; often fasting.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Starre aboue the Starres, a Sonne of light,</l>
                        <l>Whose blessed beames this wretched earth bespred</l>
                        <l>With hope of Heauen and of Gods sonne the sight</l>
                        <l>Which in our flesh and sinfull soule lay dead,</l>
                        <l>O fayth, O hope, O ioyes renownd for euer,</l>
                        <l>O liuely lyfe that deathlesse shall perseuer.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then let vs sing the lullabyes of sleepe,</l>
                        <l>To this sweet babe, borne to awake vs all,</l>
                        <l>From drowsie sinne that made old Adam weepe,</l>
                        <l>And by his fault gaue to mankinde the fall,</l>
                        <l>For loe this day, the byrth day, day of dayes,</l>
                        <l>Somons our songs to giue him laud &amp; praise.</l>
                        <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="41" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:136"/>
                     <head>Of 6. A Dialogue betwen two Sheperds. XLI. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> WHo made thee Hob, &amp;c. </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="42" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:136"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XLII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND think ye Nymphes to scorne at Loue, to scorne at loue, as if his fire were but of strawes, were but of strawes, he made, he made the mightie Gods aboue to stoope &amp; bow vnto his lawes, &amp; with his shaft of beautie bright, he slayes the harts y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> scorne his might▪ that scorne his myght, that scorne his myght. And with his shaft of beautie bright, he slayes the harts that scorne his myght, that scorne his myght, t</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:137"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XLIII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oue is a fit of pleasure, of pleasure, bread out of Idle braynes, his fancies haue no measure, no more then haue his paines: his fond affections lyke the wether, his fond affectiōs lyke the wether, precise or fond, or fond, precise or fond, we wot not whether. we wot not wether.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="44" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:137"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. XLIIII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> IF in thine hart thou nourish will and giue all to thy lust, then sorowes sharpe &amp; griefes at length, {repeat} at length, endure of force thou must: {repeat} but if that reason rule thy will, thy will, and gouerne all thy minde, all thy mynde, a blessed life then shalt thou leade, {repeat} and fewest daungers finde, daungers finde, and fewest daungers finde, {repeat} {repeat} fewest daungers finde, and fewest daungers finde, daungers finde.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="45" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:138"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. XLV. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto the hills myne eyes I lyft, my hope shall neuer fade, but from the Lord I looke for helpe, that Heauen and earth hath made: {repeat} Thy foote he will from ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping saue, he will from slypping saue, and he that doth thee keepe, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> doth thee keepe, with watchfull eye will thee preserue, {repeat} without slomber or sleepe. {repeat} The Lord thy keeper and shade is, and stands at thy right arme, the Sunne by day shall not thee burne, nor Moone by nyght thee harme. The Lord shall keepe thee from all yll, thy soule he shall preserue, {repeat} and all thy waies both in &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:176435:138"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> out, {repeat} in and out, for euer shall con╌serue. {repeat} for euer shall conserue, {repeat} {repeat} for euer shall conserue, shall con╌serue,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="46" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:139"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The first part. XLVI. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> CHrist rising againe. Death from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, {repeat} hath no power vppon him, to put a╌way sinne, {repeat} And so likewise count your selues dead vnto sinne, dead vnto sinne, but lyuing vnto God, vnto God, In Christ Iesus our Lord, in Christ Iesus our Lord.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="47" type="song">
                     <pb facs="tcp:176435:139"/>
                     <head>Of 6. voc. The second part. XLVII. BASSVS.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> CHrist is risen againe, &amp;c. Christ is risen againe, a╌gaine, Christ is risen againe, the first fruits of them that sleep, of thē that sleepe. foreseing, that by man came death, by man came death. for as by Adam, Adā, all men do dye, all men do dye, do dye. So by Christ, so by Christ, by Christ, all men shalbe restored to lyfe, all men shalbe restored to life, {repeat} restored to life, to life, restored to lyfe, to lyfe, restored to lyfe. A╌men.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:140"/>
                  <head>¶ <hi>A Table of all the songs contained in these Bookes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 3. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>LOrd in thy rage. I</item>
                        <item>Right blest are they. II</item>
                        <item>Lord in thy wrath. III</item>
                        <item>O God which art most mercifull. IIII</item>
                        <item>Lord heare my prayer instantly. V</item>
                        <item>From depth of sinne O Lord. VI</item>
                        <item>Attend myne humble prayer Lord. VII</item>
                        <item>Susanna fayre. VIII</item>
                        <item>The Nightingale. IX</item>
                        <item>When yonglings first. 1 part. X</item>
                        <item>But when by proofe. 2 part. XI</item>
                        <item>Vppon a sommers day. 1 part. XII</item>
                        <item>Then for a bote. 2 part. XIII</item>
                        <item>The greedy Hauke. XIIII</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 4. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>IS Loue a boy. 1 part. XV</item>
                        <item>Boy pittie mee. 2 part. XVI</item>
                        <item>Wounded I am. 1 part. XVII</item>
                        <item>Yet of vs twaine. 2 part. XVIII</item>
                        <item>From Citheron. 1 part. XIX</item>
                        <item>There carelesse thoughts 2 part. XX</item>
                        <item>If Loue be iust. 3 part. XXI</item>
                        <item>O Lord my God. XXII</item>
                        <item>While that the Sunne. XXIII</item>
                        <item>Reioyce, reioyce. XXIIII</item>
                        <item>Cast of all doubtfull care. XXV</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 5. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>WEeping full sore. XXVI</item>
                        <item>Penelope. XXVII</item>
                        <item>Compell y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Hauke to sit. XXVIII</item>
                        <item>See, see those sweet eyes. XXIX</item>
                        <item>When I was otherwise then now I am. XXX</item>
                        <item>When first by force. XXXI</item>
                        <item>I thought that loue had bene a boy. XXXII</item>
                        <item>O deere lyfe when may it be. XXXIII</item>
                        <item>Loue would discharge. XXXIIII</item>
                        <item>From Virgins wombe. XXXV</item>
                        <item>Of gold all burnisht. 1. part. XXXVI</item>
                        <item>Her breath is more sweet. 2. part. XXXVII</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of 6. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>BEhold how good a thing it is, 1 part. XXXVIII</item>
                        <item>And as the pleasant mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dew. 2 part. XXXIX</item>
                        <item>An earthly tree. XL</item>
                        <item>Who made thee Hob. XLI</item>
                        <item>And think ye Nymphes. 1. part. XLII</item>
                        <item>Loue is a fit of pleasure. 2. part. XLIII</item>
                        <item>If in thine hart. XLIIII</item>
                        <item>Vnto the hills. XLV</item>
                        <item>Christ rising againe. 1 part. XLVI</item>
                        <item>Christ is risen againe. 2. part. XLVII</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London by Thomas East, dwelling in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dersgate streete, at the signe of the blacke Horse.</hi> 1589.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176435:140"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>